<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Faith and good vvorkes vnited in a sermon preached at the Spittle vpon VVednesday in Easter weeke, 1630. By Richard Reeks minister of the word at Little Ilford, in Essex.</title>
            <author>Reeks, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10556</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115772</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850990</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850990</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16241</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10556)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16241)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1556:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Faith and good vvorkes vnited in a sermon preached at the Spittle vpon VVednesday in Easter weeke, 1630. By Richard Reeks minister of the word at Little Ilford, in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Reeks, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper, for Iohn Harrigat, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Holy Lambe in Pater Noster Row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXXX. [1630]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16241:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16241:1"/>
            <p>FAITH AND GOOD VVORKES Vnited: IN A SERMON PREACHED at the <hi>Spittle</hi> vpon Wedneſday in Eaſter weeke, 1630.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD REEKS Miniſter of the word at Little <hi>Ilford,</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by THOMAS HARPER, for IOHN HARRIGAT, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Holy Lambe in <hi>Pater Noſter</hi> Row, <hi>MDCXXX.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16241:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16241:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, SIR THOMAS FANSHAVV, Knight, Grace and Glory.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Haue made bold to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this Sermon to you, for that as your affection to Religion, loue to learning, hatred of ſuperſtition and ſchiſme, hath rightly honored you; ſo alſo you proceed euery way to adorne your eminent calling; <hi>Praero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gativam generis ſimilitudo morum magis ſibi vendicat quàm ordo maiorum:</hi> The congruity of manners, not the pedegree of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors,
<pb facs="tcp:16241:3"/>hath the prerogatiue of noble birth; wherein although you may plead both, yet you are more dignified by the former. The Lord hath exalted you to eminent place in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, wherein you haue approoued your ſelfe faithfull to God and his Church, ſo that you are of the number of thoſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Agapet.</note> which are able to doe good, not which need good to bee donne vnto. That therefore which is herein required as touching doing good in this contemplatiue but cold age you haue both in generall and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, ſo well performed, that you ſtand as a Lampe burning, and light ſhining vnto others to follow your worthy example; wherein no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing remaineth, but that you be found faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (as you haue beene) vnto death, that God may giue vnto you a crowne of life, ſuch ſhall the prayers of him be for you and yours, which reſteth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips in the beſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice euer to be commanded, RICHARD REEKS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16241:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Auſpicante Deo, Textus legitur in Pſalmo xxxvij. verſ. 3.</hi> Truſt in the Lord, and doe good, ſo ſhalt thou dwell in the Land, and verily thou ſhalt be fed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no faith where there is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes or hopes; difficulties and impoſſibilities are the true obiects of beleefe. Gods charges are oftentimes harſh in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and proceeding, but in the concluſion alwayes comfortable. God deferres on purpoſe, that our trials may be perfect, our deliuerance wellcome, our recompence glorious. This knew the holy Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, the Prophet Dauid right well, and therefore through more then much experience penned this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatory Song or Pſalme, as it plainly appeareth by the argument of it throughout. Wherein the Princely Prophet moſt grauely preuenteth many diſtruſtfull doubts and feares which might (in the contemplation of Chriſtianity &amp; the compariſon of the ſame with the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16241:4"/>preſent gliding delight of the wicked) at any time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe in the minds of Gods ſeruants and followers.</p>
            <p>Here by the way it may bee eaſie to obſerue how hard a thing it is to be a Chriſtian. In this reſpect his meditation affording him not more griefe then won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And here to keepe his ſtation is hard, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue harder.</p>
            <p>One while he ſcarce reſtraineth his vnruly deſires from euill; ofter can finde no liſt to good; ſometime he purpoſeth well; and when thoſe thoughts (not his) begin to lift him from the earth, loe, hee that rules in the ayre, ſtoops vpon him with powerfull temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or the world puls him downe with a ſweet vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: ſo that it is hard to ſay whether he be forced or perſwaded to yeeld; here is much weakneſſe, more trechery: good duties ſeeme harſh, and can hardly eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the repulſe, or delay of excuſes; and not without much ſtrife grow to any relliſh of pleaſure; and at the beſt cannot auoid the mixture of many infirmities.</p>
            <p>But this is not all. O God! what aduerſaries haſt thou prouided for vs, weake men? What difficulties? What encounters? Malitious and ſubtle ſpirits, an allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring world, a Serpentine and ſtubborne nature, diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full feare, neither the leaſt nor laſt enemie of mankind, which though our eyes behold, yet with ſuch amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (becauſe croſſing carnall reaſon) that from hence ariſeth eyther a ſlauiſh feare, whereby (when we ſee the number and the happineſſe of the wicked) we (like co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly Iſraelites) are ready to flie, and plead their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for our feare: who is able to ſtand before the ſons of Anak?</p>
            <p>Or, if not feare, ſo that (as we can) we weakly reſiſt, yet are we foyled with indignation and enuie, fretting our ſelues becauſe of the vngodly and being malicious againſt the euill doers, verſ. 1.</p>
            <p>Or (which is worſt of all) heereby we are ſo ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16241:4"/>that (fayth for a while ſeeming not to haue any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) impious and prophane Atheiſme ſtealing on vs, maketh this queſtion, whether there bee a God? or whether blinde chance and fatall neceſſity and fortune doe not hand ouer head moderate all things heere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. So that at ſome time or other it is hard euen for a beleeuer not to be an Infidell (at leaſt in conceit) loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king carnally to haue God at a bent: and if hee come not at a call, how eaſie to caſt him off? and to betake vs to our owne (no leſſe idolatrous then ridiculous ſhifts) like the Chinois, whipping their gods when they anſwer not.</p>
            <p>Whereas (as the Prophet heere exhorteth) his holy ones wait long, and ſeeke him; and not onely in their ſinking, but from the bottome of the deepes, call vpon him, and though hee kill them, ſtill put their truſt in him.</p>
            <p>To which purpoſe in this text is ſayd: Truſt thou in the Lord &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It is not my purpoſe to ſpend any time in ſpeaking concerning the authour of this ſacred hymne, who (as it appeareth by the argument of it) was Dauid the King: neyther will I inſiſt vpon that excellent order Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betically heere vſed, for the auoyding of tedious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixity according to the number of the Hebrew letters.</p>
            <p>The Hebrewes in their ſongs (as it might be ſhewed) did follow the method Alphabeticall, as ſome thinke, heereby to helpe the memory.</p>
            <p>Others, as <hi>Vatab.</hi> tell vs, there is no certayne reaſon of this verſifying. <hi>Apparet vulgatam carminis rationem fuiſſe.</hi> It appeares to be an ancient and vulgar cuſtome.</p>
            <p>Others as <hi>Hierom,</hi> auerre, that they were written in Saphick verſes, to which purpoſe hee alleadgeth <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Philo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others ſuppoſe this order was vſed not onely to help the memory, but alſo to note the worthineſſe of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16241:5"/>matter. And this laſt opinion may we in this place firſt of all incline vnto: this Pſalme being, <hi>Alphabetum quoddam pijs omnibus diſcendum vt nouerint vbi ſita ſit foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitas &amp; beatitudo,</hi> as <hi>Vatab.</hi> elſewhere.</p>
            <p>Heere the care of the holy Ghoſt is eſpecially to bee noted, for mans ſaluation, not onely to make the way moſt plaine for vnderſtanding, but alſo the Scriptures as familiar as our <hi>A. B. C.</hi> for our beſt conſeruing and retayning in our memory. So that this Pſalme is like Habakuks viſion, he that runneth may read a lecture of comfort in euery letter, and may moreouer well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what he readeth.</p>
            <p>But what ſhould I ſtay on that of S. <hi>Hierom.</hi> in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to <hi>Paulus Vrbicus,</hi> diuiding the whole Alphabet into ſeuen connexions; interpreteth the two and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty letters of the Croſſe-row. <hi>Aleph, doctrina. Beth, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Gimel, ſapientia &amp;c.</hi> What ſeeke we further? Heer is true wiſedome to be found.</p>
            <p>Nay, not onely methodicall but muſicall, not onely for information, but alſo for conſolation; wherefore in the words of a Prophet, Comfort ye, comfort ye, my people, and, ô yee people be ye comforted.</p>
            <p>In this conſolatory cordiall of comfort, then (for ſo wee may well call this diuine dittie one of the ſweete ſongs of Sion) we may obſerue foure parts
<list>
                  <item>1. a propoſition.</item>
                  <item>2. a confirmation.</item>
                  <item>3. an amplification.</item>
                  <item>4. a concluſion.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Prophet Dauid continually exerciſed with the croſſe, and toſſed with trouble, moſt diuinely fortifieth the mindes of all Gods children againſt any wicked aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, eſpeciallie againſt the ſcandall of the croſſe. Namelie, that no man from the outward affluence of all things, the concurrence of all outward bleſſings, all pompe, plentie, proſperitie to the hearts deſire in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16241:5"/>greateſt meaſure whatſoeuer: beholding this (as the moſt doe) onely with the carnall eye of the body, bee ſo voyd of diuine iudgement to draw this argument, Becauſe high among men, <hi>ergo</hi> high in the fauour of God.</p>
            <p>Whereas Solomon telleth vs, time and chance fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth alike to all: and our Sauiour, that God cauſeth the Sunne to ſhine on the iuſt and vniuſt. Such an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then were abſurd in Gods ſchoole, not grounded aright according to the rules of holy writ.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, becauſe the Church of God repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in euery child of God, is like Noahs Arke on the waues of the world, toſſed to and fro with contrary winds and waues, ſometimes in Shiloh, ſometimes in Keriath-iearim, ſometimes amongſt the Philiſtines, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, oppreſſed, deſtitute, not hauing like Noahs Doue where to reſt the ſole of his foot till hee land on Ararat the holy hill of heauen.</p>
            <p>If any one therefore, looking only through the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of nature, ſhould from carnall reaſon hence conclude, Becauſe this man is in miſery expoſed to trouble and calamity, <hi>ergo</hi> deſpiſed and reiected of God.</p>
            <p>This were as vncharitable as miſerable, for the holy Ghoſt hath in this place, and in many more teacheth vs to conclude otherwiſe. For all that will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus muſt ſuffer perſecution. To bee exerciſed with the croſſe is a good argument of one of his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, which by the croſſe went vnto his crowne; for thoſe that ſuffer with him, nay for him, ſhall alſo reigne with him (marke this argument) if none but ſuch, what ſhall become of the iolly jinglers of the time.</p>
            <p>Solomon hath taught vs to conclude of them and their happineſſe to bee only the cracking of thornes vnder the pot, only a blaſt.</p>
            <p>But Dauid the father becauſe more acquainted with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16241:6"/>the croſſe, therefore is much more copious in this caſe, as (not to inſtance more among many) is largely for information and conſolation ſet downe in this Pſalme particularly, they ſhall be cut downe like the graſſe, and wither, verſ. 2. they ſhall be cut off, verſe 9. yet a little while, and the wicked ſhall not be, verſe 10. the Lord ſhall laugh at him, his day is comming, verſe 13. their ſword ſhall enter into their owne heart, verſe 15. they ſhall periſh and be as the fat of Lambes, into ſmoke they ſhall conſume away, verſe 20.</p>
            <p>Yet all this while the wicked is in great power and ſpreading himſelfe like a Bay tree, verſe 35.</p>
            <p>And particularly touching the godly for conſolation,</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt dwell in the land and be fed, verſe 3. hee ſhall giue thee the deſires of thy heart, verſe 4. hee ſhall bring it to paſſe, verſe 5. he ſhall bring forth thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe as the light, and thy iudgement as the noone-day, verſe 6. thou ſhalt inherit the earth, verſe 11. in the day of famine they ſhall be ſatisfied, verſe 19. the Lord vpholdeth him with his hand, verſe 24. hee ſhall helpe them and deliuer them from the wicked, verſe 40. marke the perfect man and behold the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, for the end of that is peace, verſe 37.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding all this, the iuſt and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man is in many troubles, ſo that this which Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid here affirmeth of the ſtate of either in the iudgement of fleſh and blood is a meere Paradox, and in naturall reaſon incomprehenſible, but thoſe things which are impoſſible with men, are poſſible with God, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things are ſpiritually diſcerned, wherefore</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Truſt in the Lord, and be doing good; ſo dwell in the land, and verily thou ſhalt be fed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Text we are to obſerue 2 parts,
<list>
                  <item>1 a precept, truſt in the Lord.</item>
                  <item>2 a promiſe, to dwell in the land and be fed.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:16241:6"/>
Touching the precept it hath reference
<list>
                  <item>1 to God.</item>
                  <item>2 to man.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 To God: truſt thou in the Lord; for matter of piety,</p>
            <p n="2">2 To man: and be doing good: for matter of charity.</p>
            <p>Faith and good workes are inſeparably vnited, as the ſoule and the body (yet in their order) firſt faith, for, truſt in the Lord: ſecondly good works: be doing good: whom God hath then thus ioyned together, let no man put aſunder. Now as when man and wife like faithfull yoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellowes, and like the words of my Text walke orderly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>aequis paſſibus,</hi> a happy iſſue attendeth on their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: So if our faith be grounded on God in the firſt place, and from hence we be enabled in the ſecond place to doe good, then a long Catalogue of many glorious bleſſings waiteth on vs to crowne vs, and thoſe are either
<list>
                  <item>externall,
<list>
                        <item>to dwell in the land.</item>
                        <item>to be fed.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>internall,
<list>
                        <item>to haue the deſires of his heart v. 4.</item>
                        <item>to haue abundance of peace v. 11.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>eternall,
<list>
                        <item>to dwell for euermore,</item>
                        <item>verſe 27. and 29.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Whence we ſee that thoſe which haue the Lord for their maſter, haue the moſt profitable ſeruice in the world, to whom the promiſe of this life, and ſo reſpecting the body and the ſoule in the inchoation of grace, and that which is to come: and ſo reſpecting body and ſoule in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of glory, moſt properly belongeth, for be ſaith, dwell in the land, thou ſhalt be fed; a conſtant promiſe of him whoſe word is yea and amen:</p>
            <p>Touching this Text then it may be ſayd that it compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth the Law and the Goſpell; in which wee haue the firſt and ſecond table: the ſumme of the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>viz.</hi> to loue God aboue all: which we cannot doe if we truſt not in him To loue our neighbour as our ſelues, which we cannot doe neither, if we be not doing good. So that the grace of God (like the Sonne in his glory) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in our Text to teach vs to deny all vngolineſſs, &amp;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16241:7"/>to liue religiouſly, by truſting in the Lord: righteouſly, by doing good to our ſelues and others: and ſoberly, by waiting on the Lord, dwelling in the land and being fed.</p>
            <p>In the words what obſcurity? onely the laſt, dwell in the land and thou ſhalt be fed, challenge at my hands a further interpretation; our letter not ſo well bearing, and therefore not ſo neerely anſwering the originall: of which when I come vnto the promiſe.</p>
            <p>I For the precept, as touching our faith; truſt thou in the Lord. Hauing then thus farre acquainted you with the ſcope of the holy Ghoſt, at large; that the children of God when they ſee themſelues in great miſery, and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked flouriſhing as a greene Bay tree, ought not to bee ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at this, nor to fret hereat, or be filled with indignation, or becauſe they are like a fat Oxe fatted for the day of ſlaughter, whereas the children of God muſt bee exerciſed with many afflictions; leſt with the world they ſhould be condemned. 2 That their light afflictions which are but temporall, may be crowned with glory which is eternall. And for this cauſe to truſt in the Lord, whence I obſerue, that in all troubles and trials whatſoeuer,<note place="margin">Doctr.</note> and at all times we ought confidently to truſt in the Lord.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The place is a confirmation of this truth,<note place="margin">Illuſtr.</note> as it is vſed here by way of precept, truſt thou in Iehouah.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe is that of Dauid, in God is my ſaluation and my glory, the rock of my ſtrength and my refuge is in God.</p>
            <p>Truſt in him at all times yee people, poure out your hearts before him: God is a refuge for vs. In which the Prophet not only biddeth and exhorteth vs to truſt in him, but moreouer addeth a reaſon drawne from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable effect of ſuch confidence; becauſe he is a refuge to helpe vs and deliuer vs.</p>
            <p>To this place is that of Solomon,<note place="margin">Pro. 3.5.</note> truſt in the Lord with all thy heart: and leane not to thine owne vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This hath beene the practiſe of the children of God in all troubles, and in all times, as is proued from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of that godly and faithfull King, who when the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16241:7"/>Moabites and Ammonites came againſt him, to battell, after he had prayed vnto the Lord for helpe and deliuerance, as the people went forth into the wilderneſſe of Tekoa,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 20.20.</note> Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat ſtood and ſaid: Heare me O Iudah and yee inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of Ieruſalem, truſt in the Lord your God, ſo ſhall yee be eſtabliſhed; beleeue his Prophets ſo ſhall yee proſper. An example we haue in good Iacob, who truſting in the Lord was not afraid to returne to his owne Country, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the malice which his brother Eſau had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued againſt him,<note place="margin">Gen. 31.3.</note> becauſe hee beleeued that God who commanded him to goe would alſo defend him.</p>
            <p>The like might I ſay concerning the reſt of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, Noah, Abraham, Lot, Iſaac, Ioſeph, Dauid, Daniel, together with the ſacred quire of reuerend antiquity ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned by the Author to the Hebrewes, who through faith ſubdued Kingdomes,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> wrought righteouſneſſe, obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the promiſe, ſtopped the mouth of Lions, quenched the violence of the fire, eſcaped the edge of the ſword, waxed valiant in battell, and turned to ſlight the armies of Aliants.</p>
            <p>By euidence whereof we ſee that if we truſt in God and caſt our care on him, he is ſuch a father of mercies and God of all comfort that he will alſo care for vs.</p>
            <p>For which cauſe our Sauiour ſaid to his diſciples, let not your hearts be troubled, you beleeue in God; beleeue alſo in me;<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.1.</note> &amp;c. A little faith then euen as ſmall as a graine of Muſtard ſeed, is able to make vs liſt vp our heads in the middeſt of all troubles, and to remoue euen Mountaines of diſtruſts out of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the deſcription of the ſpirituall armour faith is compared to a buckler or ſhield:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.16.</note> which guardeth eſpecially the head and heart; that is (as it may be conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) the vnderſtanding and will, <hi>ut non turbetur intellectus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diez com. <hi>1.</hi> in feſt Phil. Iacol.</note> 
               <hi>non formidet affectus,</hi> that we be not troubled in our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, nor made fearfull in our affection. By faith the children of God haue beene more bold then Lions, and enabled to doe euen all things.</p>
            <p>When Taxaris ſaw his Countriman Anacharſis in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16241:8"/>he ſaid vnto him, I will at once ſhew thee all the wonders of Greece,<note place="margin">Lucianus in Scytha.</note> 
               <hi>viſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Solone vidiſti omnia;</hi> in ſeeing So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon thou ſeeſt all, euen Athens it ſelfe, and all the glory of the Greeks. In like manner I may tell a true Chriſtian: haſt thou ſaith and aſſured truſt in the Lord? thou haſt more then all the wonders of Greece; vpon the point, all the wonderfull gifts of grace: for faith is a mother vertue from whence all other ſpring, and without which our beſt actions are but <hi>ſplendida peccata,</hi> ſhining ſinnes, Rom. 14.24. moſt neceſſary then that we truſt in the Lord.</p>
            <p>And not without great reaſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe if we truſt not in the Lord as touching grace we are dead:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </note> as long as we liue we breath and labour for life euen in death: faith is the life of grace, the death of all ſinne:<note place="margin">Hab. 2.4.</note> hence it is ſaid, the iuſt man liueth by his faith, and liuing hereby his ſoule truſteth in the Lord, hee looketh cheerfully to God, hauing the ſpirit of boldneſſe, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that we may ſay of him, <hi>Si fractus illabatur orbis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pavidum ferient ruinae,</hi> if the mountaines ſhould be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and caſt headlong into the Sea, ſtill hee ſtandeth his ground: yea, <hi>Terra fremat, regna alta crepent, ruat orcus &amp; ortus; Si modo firma fides, nulla ruina nocet.</hi> If that all the world ſhould crack in peeces, neuertheleſſe he ſtandeth faſt and firme, grounded on the rock fixed like the Mount Sion,<note place="margin">Pſal. 129.</note> not to be remoued at any time by any meanes; for he truſteth in the Lord, and vnder the ſhadow of his wings is the righteous mans refuge till the tyrannie of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.</note> ſinne, death and hell be ouerpaſt: for he hath (if I may ſo ſay) the life-blood of the ſoule, true faith in the Lord, and relieth on his promiſes and therefore cannot miſcarrie.</p>
            <p>Whereas on the other ſide, a faithleſſe man and diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all troubles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whatſoeuer, is ready not onely to ſincke vnder his burden, but alſo to giue vp the ghoſt. It is with them as it was with Nabal; a diſtruſtfull perſon hath a head like Nabal, a heart like Nabal, when he heareth of any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and croſſes not to be vndergone, but which hee hath eſcaped ignorantly.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sam. 25.37.</note> His heart preſently dieth within him, and he becommeth as a ſtone.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16241:8"/>
Phyſitians tell vs, that in mans body the arteres running along the veines, do beat vpon them, and ſtir vp the blood, leſt congeling, it ſhould waxe cold; ſo in the ſoule of the godly, true fayth beateth in time of all diſtreſſe, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth it aliue in the wicked, as in Nabal it moueth not, and therefore in neceſſity either they die with griefe, as he did, or with Achitophel hang themſelues, or with Saul run in diſtreſſe to the witch of Endor, to hell for helpe; whereas the children of God wait vpon him for deliuerance with patience and with confidence truſt in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Becauſe fayth is the only meanes wherby we apprehend all the promiſes of God,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </note> and apply them to our comfort in time of need: hence it is that the Apoſtle S. Paul (or els who) to the Hebrewes, ſayth,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> Without fayth it is impoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to pleaſe God. For hee that commeth to God, muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that he is, and that he is a rewarder (or as our purpoſe is, a deliuerer) of them that diligently ſeeke him.</p>
            <p>So then without faith, no apprehenſion of God as he is: without apprehenſion, no deliuerance.</p>
            <p>Faith then is the meanes: and God vſually ſhapeth the end according to the meanes. Naaman had neuer beene cleanſed of his leproſie, if he had not beene waſhed in Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dane. God is not tied to meanes, but men are, which wee both may and muſt vſe, if we expect or deſire the iſſue. God could ſauevs without the preaching of his word, but he will not. Hee hath ordayned no meanes ſo effectuall to beget fayth as this; and therefore we muſt haue a conſtant depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance thereon.</p>
            <p>God could raiſe vp children to Abraham from the ſtones: he could of Diuels and reprobates make Saints and Angels, but he will not; it is one thing what hee can doe, another what he will doe. And therefore monſtrous abſurdities might be concluded, if that we ſhould diſpute from his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to his will.</p>
            <p>It is well taken that the father of the Prodigall would neither fetch the robe nor ſuffer his ſon to fetch it neither, but commanded his ſeruants to bring it foorth and put it on: and why? If not to bring meanes into credit, for which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16241:9"/>the Goſpell aboundeth with examples; in all thoſe mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous deliuerances wrought by our Sauior aſcribing them ſtill to fayth.</p>
            <p>Hence when Peter began to ſincke, hee attributeth it to his in fidelity and diſtruſt, in that he ſayd, O thou of little fayth! wherefore didſt thou doubt? As if hee had ſayd, if thou hadſt truſted in me,<note place="margin">Mat. 14.31.</note> thou couldſt not haue miſcarried.</p>
            <p>And in another place it is ſayd, he could doe no works there, becauſe of their vnbeleefe, ſaue that he laid his hands vpon a few ſicke. On the other ſide, in many miracles, we finde the truth of this point confirmed.</p>
            <p>When the diſtreſſed woman of Canaan whoſe daughter was miſerably vexed with a Diuell cried vnto him for help,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.28.</note> ſaying, Haue mercy on me, O Lord, thou ſonne of Dauid, &amp;c. whom for importunities ſake, the Diſciples beſought to ſend her away: he anſwered, I am not ſent but to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>Then came the woman and worſhipped, ſaying; Lord helpe me; to whom hee replied, It is not meete to take the childrens bread, and to caſt it to the dogges. And ſhe ſayd, truth Lord, yet the dogs eate the crummes which fall from their maſters table. (Hence the deliuerance) O woman, great is thy faith! be it vnto thee as thou wilt, and her daughter was made whole.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe the Leper that came vnto him, beſeeching him and kneeling downe vnto him; ſaid, If thou wilt thou canſt make me whole, (behold his faith and ſee deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) Ieſus moued with compaſſion, put forth his hand and touched him,<note place="margin">Mark. 1.40.</note> and ſaid, I will, be thou whole, and hee was cleanſed.</p>
            <p>Againe, in him which was ſick of the palſie, we ſee the ſame thing, when they could not come nigh vnto him for the preſſe,<note place="margin">Mark. 2.4.5.</note> they vncouered the roofe where he was, and let downe the bed where the ſick of the palſie lay. When Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaw their faith, he ſaid vnto the ſick of the palſie, ſonne thy ſinnes be forgiuen thee.</p>
            <p>So the woman with the bloody iſſue, hauing beene troubled twelue yeeres, and ſpent all on Phyſitians, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16241:9"/>become much worle; when ſhe had but touched his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (for note her faith, ſhe had ſaid, if I touch but his clothes I ſhall be whole) the fountaine of her blood was dried vp,<note place="margin">Mark. 5.25.</note> and ſhe was healed of that plague. And all this is aſcribed to her faith, daughter thy faith hath made thee whole, goe in peace.</p>
            <p>The like is to be inſtanced in the deliuerance vouchſafed vnto Iairus in his daughter, when the people told him ſhe was dead, why troubleſt thou the maſter?<note place="margin">Mark. 5.36.</note> Ieſus ſaid vnto the Ruler of the Synagogue, be not afraid, onely beleeue: and he raiſed her.</p>
            <p>So in the miracle wrought vpon the mans ſonne which was dumbe, the deliuerance is aſcribed to faith, in that our Sauiour ſaid all things are poſſible,<note place="margin">Mark. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> if thou canſt beleeue. And the father of the child cryed with teares, I beleeue, Lord helpe my vnbeleefe, and then and thus hee cured him.</p>
            <p>Plaine for this purpoſe is that of blind Bartimeus the ſonne Timeus alſo, who hearing that Ieſus paſſed by, cried out, Ieſus thou ſonne of Dauid haue mercy on me. What wouldeſt thou, ſaid Chriſt?<note place="margin">Mark. 10.46.</note> Lord that I might receiue my ſight; to whom he anſwered, goe thy way, thy faith hath made thee whole.</p>
            <p>So the Leper which was cleanſed, goe thy way,<note place="margin">Luk. 17.14.</note> thy faith hath made thee whole.</p>
            <p>So to the woman which brake an Alabaſter box of oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſtood at his feet weeping, and waſhing them with her teares, and wiping them with her haires, and kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them, and anointing them, and being a ſinner; to whom Chriſt ſaid, thy ſinnes, which are many, are forgiuen,<note place="margin">Luk. 7.50.</note> but whence this vnſpeakable mercy? hence, thy faith hath ſaued thee, goe in peace.</p>
            <p>Whence it not from hence alſo was that miraculous rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Centurions ſeruant as it were from death? euen from bis faith: he had built a Synagogue he ſaid in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Lord trouble not thy ſelfe, for I am not worthy that thou ſhouldeſt enter vnder my roofe, neither thought I my ſelfe worthy to come vnto thee,<note place="margin">Luk. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> onely ſay the word
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16241:10"/>and my ſeruant ſhall be healed. Whereupon our Sauiour, verily I ſay vnto you, I haue not found ſo great faith, no not in Iſrael, and ſo he cured her.</p>
            <p>But why wade I ſo farre into the Sanctuary for teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to proue this? when as among ſo many it is hard not to be infinite. In a word our Sauiour moſt diuinely, not only by example, but poſitiuely by precept confirmeth and concluded this point. When his diſciples maruelled that the tree which he curſed was withered away, hee ſaid to them, haue faith in God, for I ſay vnto you, whoſoeuer ſhall ſay vnto this mountaine, be thou remoued, and bee thou caſt into the ſea, and ſhall beleeue that thoſe things which he ſaith ſhall come to paſſe, ſhall haue whatſoeuer he ſaith.<note place="margin">Mar. 11.23.24.</note> And whatſoeuer ye ſhall deſire when yee pray, beleeue ye ſhall receiue them and ye ſhall haue them.</p>
            <p>Thus then ſeeing ſo much is attributed to faith as you haue heard, it we would be deliuered, we muſt truſt in the Lord, and that for this reaſon drawne from the profitable end which followeth, namely, to bee deliuered: on the contray, the meanes neglected, no maruell if the end be not obtained.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon: </seg>3</label> Becauſe this is the commandement of God, namely. that we truſt in him here poſitiuely; imperatively, truſt thou in Iehouah: this is pointed out with the finger of God vnto vs in the firſt commandement. Thou ſhalt haue no other Gods but me, wherein we are commanded to worſhip God and him alone, which worſhip ſtandeth on theſe ſoure pillars,
<list>
                  <item>1 louing God aboue all.</item>
                  <item>2 fearing God aboue all.</item>
                  <item>3 praying to God, and none but him.</item>
                  <item>4 in acknowledging God to be the guider of all things, and therefore to truſt in him.</item>
               </list>
which, though the laſt, is not the leaſt in the affirmatiue part of this precept.</p>
            <p>It is commanded oftentimes in other place of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as in Proverb. 3.5. <hi>fiduciam habe in Iehova ex toto cordetu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> in Pſal. 4.5. offer the ſacrifice of righteouſneſſe,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16241:10"/>and put your truſt in the Lord, in the 5. verſe alſo of the 37. Plalme, <hi>Devolve ſuper Iehovam viam tuam, &amp; confide in eo,</hi> commit thy way &amp;c. in Pſal. 62.8. truſt in him at all times, ye people poure out your hearts before him: God is a refuge for vs. (this is worthy to bee noted with no leſſe then Selah) in Iſay 26.4. truſt ye in the Lord for euer: for in the Lord Iehovah is euerlaſting ſtrength.</p>
            <p>This then is the diuine voice of God, <hi>dixit Dominus,</hi> which him ſelfe hath ſaid (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and as hee hath ſpoke by the mouth of his holy Prophets ſince the world began; which command implyes obedience.</p>
            <p>The Rechabites are commended by the Prophet Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah for that they obeyed the commandement of Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab the ſonne of Rechab,<note place="margin">Iere: 35.8.</note> in abſtayning from wine all their dayes, and in dwelling in tents; for which obedience the Lord promiſed that Ionadab the ſonne of Rechab ſhould not want a man to ſtand before him for euer.</p>
            <p>I inferre from the Rechabites, if wee faithfully truſt in the Lord, as not Ionadab a mortall man, but the high and moſt mighty Iehouah hath commanded vs, we ſhall ſtand before him for euer, we ſhall dwell in the land and bee fed in faith foreuermore.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> Becauſe of the infinite profit which acreweth to thoſe that truſt in the Lord: ſo teſtifieth Solomon,<note place="margin">Pro. 22.18.19.</note> for it is a pleaſant thing if thou keepe them within thee, they ſhall be fitted in thy lips, that thy truſt may be in the Lord &amp;c. Againe, he that truſteth in the Lord ſhall be made fat, that is, he ſhall be enriched with all the bleſſings of God.<note place="margin">Prou. 28.25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>So we ſee that thoſe which truſted in the Lord haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies proſpered and obtained victory of their enemies; hitherto is that memorable victory of the people of Iudah ouer the Iſraelites to be referred,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 13.18.</note> when God deliuered them into their hand, and they ſlew of Iſrael fiue hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand choſen men. And the reaſon is there rendred, becauſe the men of Iſrael had forſaken the Lord and truſted rather in the calues of Ieroboam the ſonne of Nebat, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Iſrael to ſinne: whereas the people of Iudah kept the charge of the Lord their God, and did truſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16241:11"/>
Hitherto is that notable victory of Aſa to bee referred, in theſe words Hanan the Seer challengeth Aſa the King Iudah hauing made a league with Benhadad King of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 16.7.</note> Becauſe thou haſt relied on Benhadad King of Syria, and not relied on the Lord thy God: therefore is the hoſt of the King of Syria eſcaped thy hand.</p>
            <p>Were not the Aethiopians and the Lubims a huge hoſt,<note place="margin">Verſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> with very many charrets and horſemen? yet becauſe thou didſt rely on the Lord, he deliuered them into thy hand.</p>
            <p>And yet behold a greater profit, for confidence in God bringeth tranquility, and ſecurity, and peace of conſcience, as is ſhewed in the example of Dauid, I layd me downe and ſlept, I awaked, for the Lord ſuſtained me. I will not be afraid for ten thouſands of people that haue ſet themſelues againſt me round about.<note place="margin">Pſal. 3.6.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, confidence in God <hi>omnigenam benedictionem homini praeſtat,</hi> procureth all manner of bleſſings. A plaine and comfortable proofe is that of the holy Prophet, in theſe words,<note place="margin">Ier. 17.7.8.</note> Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in the Lord, and whoſe hope the Lord is.</p>
            <p>For he ſhall be as a tree planted by the waters, and that ſpreadeth out her roots by the riuer, and ſhall not ſee when heat commeth, but her leafe ſhall be greene, and ſhall not be carefull in the yeere of drought, neither ſhall ceaſe from yeelding fruit.</p>
            <p>So Dauid:<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.7.</note> for the King truſteth in the Lord; therefore through the mercy of the moſt high he ſhall not be moued.</p>
            <p>Againe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 125.1.2.</note> they that truſt in the Lord ſhall be as the mount Sion, which cannot be mooued for euer.</p>
            <p>This was the promiſe which the Lord made vnto Ebed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech the Ethiopian that when he accompliſhed his word in bringing euill vpon the city, that he ſhould be deliuered and not be giuen into the hand of the men of whom hee was afrayd:<note place="margin">Ier. 39.17.18.</note> for I will ſurely deliuer thee, thou ſhalt not fall by the ſword, but thy life ſhall be a prey vnto thee.</p>
            <p>And why all this mercy? Becauſe thou haſt put thy truſt in me, ſayth the Lord. In reſpect of the great profit and the exceeding great reward that followeth our confidence.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16241:11"/>Good reaſon that we truſt in the Lord:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>5</label> Becauſe of the prouidence of Iehouah whereby hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth and preſerueth thoſe that truſt in him. Hence, ſaith Dauid, I will lay mee downe in peace and ſleepe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.8.</note> for thou Lord only makeſt me dwell in ſafety. Thou by thy proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence preſerueſt me. Hence is that of Eſay;<note place="margin">Iſay. 26 4.</note> Truſt in the Lord for euer; for in the Lord Iehouah is euerlaſting ſtrength. Hence is that of our Sauiour; Take no thought for your life, what you ſhall eat or drinke, or what you ſhall put on. Behold the fowles of the ayre, for they ſow nor,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.26.28.</note> nor reape, nor gather into barnes; yet your heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feedeth them. Are yee not much better then they? Conſider the Lillies of the field how they grow, they toile not, neither ſpin, yet Salomon in his glory was not clothed like one of theſe. Wherefore if God ſo cloath the graſſe of the field, which to day is, and to morrow is caſt into the ouen, ſhall hee not much more cloth you, ô yee of little fayth? After theſe things the Gentiles ſeeke: as if hee had ſayd, you that know God and his prouidence ought not to be like the Gentiles, which becauſe they know not God, therefore truſt not in God.</p>
            <p>If he ſo well prouide for the Rauens when they call vpon him, how much more ſhall hee prouide for his children that put their truſt in him.</p>
            <p>Some Philoſophers thought it too great a labor for God to gouerne the whole world: and other on the contrarie too baſe. But diuines anſwer them both in one word;<note place="margin">Apud Ambroſ. de offic. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Deus u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que laborat in maximis neque faſtidit in minimis. Amb. in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xam lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. Indeed the Poet ſayd,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non vacat exigu is rebus adeſſe Iovi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Scripture otherwiſe, that the very haires of our head are numbred,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.30.</note> and that not ſo much as a ſparrow which is ſold for a farthing can fall on the ground, without our heauenly fathers prouidence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diſponit membraculicis &amp; pulicis,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Pſal.</hi> 148.</note> For beſides his generall prouidence which is ſeene in the gouernment of the whole vniuerſe,<note place="margin">Calvin. Inſtis. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> he hath a ſpeciall alſo mode rating euery ſingular action and accident. Who dwelling on
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16241:12"/>high,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquin.</hi> 1. <hi>part. quaeſt.</hi> 22. <hi>art.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; Caiet. ibid.</hi> Heb. 1.3. Wiſd. 8.1.</note> beholdeth vs as Emmots vpon the mole hils of the earth, in whom we liue and moue and haue our being.</p>
            <p>For it is written, he ſupporteth all things by his mighty word. He reacheth from one end to another, and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things ſweetly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnia non ſolum permiſſa à Deo, ſed etiam immiſſa,</hi> as one ſaith:<note place="margin">Lip ſius Conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> ſo that nothing falleth out by blinde humane chance but by diuine choiſe.</p>
            <p>The Lord doeth not onely ſuffer and ſee what is done heere below, but alſo diſpoſeth of euery particular euent to the glory of his name, and good of his children. He beheld Dauid in his trouble, Daniel in his dungeon, Peter in his priſon, and ordered their ſhort affliction to their endleſſe conſolation.</p>
            <p>In that then though he dwelleth on high hee humbleth himſelfe to behold the things below. In that he keepeth Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,<note place="margin">Pſal. 121.4.</note> which doth neither ſlumber nor ſleepe.</p>
            <p>In that he graueth his children on the palmes of his hands.<note place="margin">Iſay. 49.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In that he heareth the very grones of his children in their cloſets,<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.9.</note> and maketh their beds in their ſickneſſe, Pſal. 41.3.</p>
            <p>In that (as Auguſtine ſweetly) hee taketh care for all his children as if all were but one;<note place="margin">Confeſ. l. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> and for euery particular as if one were all. Becauſe of this diuine and moſt bleſſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, Truſt in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Vnto theſe we might further adde many more forcible reaſons, grounded on the perſon, in my text; as namely, ſixthly, from the power; ſeuenthly, from the mercy; eight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from the loue; ninthly, from the wiſdome; tenthly, from the goodneſſe; adde alſo the truth of Iehouah; and looke how many meditations you may conceiue concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God, ſo many reaſons you haue to Truſt in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer he is, he is it to vs, and for vs; becauſe hee is the Lord Iehouah, our God; wherefore let vs truſt in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thus farre of the Doctrine and the Illuſtration thereof, by Scripture and by reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:16241:12"/>
Proceed wee now to the vſe of this Doctrine, which is diuerſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> It ſerueth firſt for our information,<note place="margin">I. Iohn. 14.1.</note> we ought alwayes to truſt in Iehouah. Our Sauiour ſo enformeth and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his diſciples, Let not your hearts be troubled; yee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in the father, beleeue alſo in me; in whatſoeuer dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of ſoule or of body, of life or of death ye may bee, yet be not diſcouraged, but truſt in the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doloſum &amp; aerumnoſum eſt cor hominis,</hi> as the heart of man is aboue all things deceitfull, ſo is it diſtruſtfull. For as S. <hi>Baſill</hi> to this purpoſe ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Pſal.</hi> 44.</note> we are of one condition in proſperity, but of another in aduerſitie; as it is moſt plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exemplified vnto vs in that example of Peter in Matth. 26.33.69.</p>
            <p>Fortune (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) freeth many from puniſhment,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 61. <hi>&amp;</hi> 79.</note> but none from feare; many and manifold dangers like waues comming faſt one on the backe of another, one griefe calling on another, as the clouds burſt foorth with raine.</p>
            <p>Many and fearfull are thoſe dangers whereunto the life of man is liable; yet if God be for vs, what ſhall be againſt vs? if our truſt be grounded on the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.2.3.4.</note> if our confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence be ſure, we need not feare though the earth bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, and though the mountaines be caſt into the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the Sea, though the waters thereof roare and bee troubled, though the mountaines ſhake with the ſwelling thereof, though the world be lifted off the hinges, and all things be turned vpſide downe, though all things goe the cleane contrary way; in a word though the Sunne be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into darkneſſe, and the Moone into blood, though the pillars of the earth and the powers of heauen be ſhaken, yea, though the frame of the world, like the temple of Dagon, fall ratling vpon our heads, yet we will not feare, for as Dauid ſaith, Pſal. 18.2. The Lord is my rocke, and my fortreſſe, and my deliuerer: my God, my ſtrengh, in whom I will truſt: my buckler and the horne of my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and my high tower.</p>
            <p>God is our Captaine, therefore like Souldiers wee will
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16241:13"/>rely vpon his warineſſe and watchfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>God is our Shepheard, therefore like ſheepe wee ſhall ſleepe in peace vnder his ſtaffe.</p>
            <p>God is our Pilot, therefore like paſſengers ſayling in great waters we ſhall be without feare vnder the protection of his care and experience.</p>
            <p>God is our King, therefore like ſubiects we will feare no inuaſion of enemies no want of prouiſion vnder his ſo well-ordered gouernment.</p>
            <p>God is our father, therefore like to his children we will feare no ill vnder his armes. O truſt in the Lord, for he is the Lord of hoſts.<note place="margin">1 Sam 15.45.</note> Antigonus King of Syria (as Plutarch ſpeaketh) being ready to giue battell by ſea bard by the Iſle Andros,<note place="margin">In Pelopida.</note> anſwered one of his men, who told him that his enemies had more ſhips then he, For how many men rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koneſt thou me? indeed the dignity of the Generall is much to be eſteemed when it is ſorted with proweſſe and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. But where is there proweſſe, where experience, if it be not in the Lord? Therefore Iob excellently ſaith, hee is wiſe in heart, and mighty in ſtrength. Who hath hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned himſelfe againſt him and hath proſpered? Iob. 9.4.</p>
            <p>Surely ſaith Dauid Pſal. 3.8. Saluation belongeth vnto the Lord. And the Prophet Eſay ſaith, Eſay 43.11, I, euen I, am he, and beſides me there is no Sauiour. For as none can deliuer out of his hand, ſo none can deliuer as he can. To the righteous he is a ſhield, Pſalme 5.12. To the weake ſtrength, Pſalme 22.12. To the oppreſſed a refuge, Pſalme 9.9. To the perſecuted a fortreſſe, Pſalme 91.2.9. To the Sun-burnt with afflictions he is a ſhadow. To thoſe that are exiled for righteouſneſſe ſake, bee is a well furniſhed habitation. To the thirſty he is a well of water, as to Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſon: To the purſued he is a wall of defence, as to the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites. To the hungry hee is the bread of life. To the faint he is a bed of downe. To the miſerable he is a deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, neither are his deliueries palliatiue cures, eaſing (as cold water in a feuer) onely for the preſent, but all together; not anodins to take away for ſome few howres the ſence of our paine, not the paine it ſelfe, but they are ſaluation, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16241:13"/>as it were reſurrections from the dead. Euen as Daniel ſaith,<note place="margin">Dan. 6.27.</note> he deliuereth and reſcueth, and hee worketh ſignes and wonders in heauen and earth.</p>
            <p>So he deliuered Iſrael our of Egypt.</p>
            <p>So he deliuered Dauid from Saul.</p>
            <p>So he deliuered Hezekias and Iehoſaphat from their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</p>
            <p>So hee deliuered Shadrach, Meſhach, and Abednego from the furnace.</p>
            <p>So he deliuered Daniel from the Den.</p>
            <p>So his people out of the Dungeon in Babylon: and ſuch hath euer been his deliuerance; O how eaſie is it to be infinite in this matter? how well might wee looſe our ſelues in the wood, rather the world of theſe wonders.</p>
            <p>Such laſtly, was his deliuerance of the Church in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land from the tyranny of the bloody Byſhop of Rome, from the Spaniſh inuaſion 88. from that mercileſſe and matchleſſe treaſon, both for fict and faction, the gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der treaſon, Nouemb. 5. 1605.</p>
            <p>O then being compaſſed about with deliuerances, ſuch deliuerances of ſuch a Lord, ſuch a Sauiour, ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. Let vs truſt in our Lord God.</p>
            <p>Let me now ſay to you all (to conclude this vſe) as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid to his people, Let Iſrael, yea, let vs all truſt in the Lord, for with the Lord there is mercy, and with our God is plenteous redemption. With him is force and a ſtrength to redeeme Iſrael out of all her troubles, he may doe it, hee can doe it, he will doe it; ſearch and looke through all ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations of men which haue beene ſince the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, and you ſhall not finde one forſaken that put his truſt in the Lord; therefore from hence foorth and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer let vs truſt in the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Thus farre of the firſt vſe for our information, a ſecond followeth for reproofe and terror. For terror, for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, Thus ſaith the Lord,<note place="margin">Ier. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.</note> Curſed be euery man that truſteth in men, and maketh fleſh his arme, for reproofe then of all thoſe which truſt not in the Lord, but in other, both tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory and tranſient meanes; ſuch there are, for,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:16241:14"/>
Some me put their truſt in vncertaine riches, and ſay to the wedge of gold, thou art my confidence; but theſe intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably offend,<note place="margin">Iob. 31.24.</note> and groſly deceiue themſelues, for riches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile not in the day of wrath.<note place="margin">Pro. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4.</note> The hoarders vp of ſiluer and gold come to nought, and goe downe to hell as it is in Baruch 3.17. O foole, this night will they fetch away thy ſoule from thee: where is now thy god? thy gold? and thy truſt? yet this cankered gold is the worldlings god, nothing more ordinary then to truſt in vncertaine riches: for the rich mans wealth is his ſtrong City, ſaith Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Now where will a man account himſelfe ſafe, but in his fort?</p>
            <p>He ſees Mammon to be a great Lord of great command; he ſees he can doe much, and heares him ſay he can doe as much more, yea all things, and now no maruayle that hee truſteth is him.</p>
            <p>Mammon is ſo proud a boaſter that his clients muſt needs be confident in him; what doth not he brag to doe? Siluer anſwers to all, ſayth Solomon. This wee grant, yet wee would be loth it could command truth, iuſtice, iudgement; yet he ſayth he can procure all, conquer all, pacifie all. He ſayes he can procure all ſecular offices, titles and dignities, yea, (in ſome ſacrilegious wretches, Simonaicall patrons) the promotions of the Church; ye remember the old ſong of the Pope, <hi>Claues, altaria, Chriſtum.</hi> Simon Magus the grand father of theſe, made full reckoning to haue bought the holy Ghoſt for mony.</p>
            <p>He ſayes he can pacifie all: a giſt pacifieth wrath. (Let them in place of iuſtice looke to it, whom it may concern) he can bribe off ſinnes, and peruert iudgement. He ſayes he can ouercome all, for ſo he ſingeth in the Poet, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Fight with Launces of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and thine ſhall bee the victory. With this weapon hee thought to foyle the ſonne of God. All theſe will I giue thee, briefly according to the French and Greeke pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, all things obey the Lord Mammon, this is a great Lord, if this be true, he ſaith the worldling beleeueth and truſteth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:16241:14"/>
But let me tell you in a word what gold can doe.</p>
            <p>He can both open and then barre the gates of hell to the vnconſcionable ſoule, and helpe his followers to dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, this he can doe, and this is all.</p>
            <p>As for other things, though the fooliſh ſiluer Smiths of the time ſhout out, great is Mammon of the worldlings, yet weigh his power in the ballance of iudgement, and you will conclude of him (as Paracelſus of the Deuill) that he is a baſe and beggarly ſpirit.</p>
            <p>For tell me I beſeech you what hee can doe? Can hee make a man honeſt? can he make him wiſe? can hee make him healthfull? can he giue to liue more merrily, to feed more heartily, to ſleepe more quietly? yea, rather will hee not procure the contrary, make diſhoneſt, fooliſh, ſick, and vnquiet.</p>
            <p>Can he buy off the gout, cares, death? much leſſe the paines of hell? Gee to now yee worldlings, God meanes to puniſh thee with death, now try what thy bags can doe? ſee if thou canſt bribe God with a gift, will the Lord bee pleaſed with thouſands of Rams? or with ten thouſand riuers of oyle? See if thou canſt bribe death the Serpent of God; he lookes thee ſternly in the face, and tels thee with Ehud his meſſage is from God, and ſheatheth his ſword in thy bowels. yet</p>
            <p>See if thou canſt bribe the Bayliffe of death, thy diſeaſe, he will tell thee as Laban, this is proceeded of God; I can therefore ſay to thee nor good nor euill. In a word, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe will ſummon thee to death, death will arreſt thee to the iudgement ſeat of God, God will paſſe his doome; and in all theſe, true is that of Solomon. Riches auaile not in the day of wrath.</p>
            <p>Thoſe therefore which make their wealth riuals with God ſhall be burned in die fire of his iealouſie; they that leane on them truſt to a reed which will not only breake, but alſo runne into their hands; for he that truſteth in riches ſhall fall.</p>
            <p>Some put their truſt in their owne worth and holineſſe, as the Phariſee,<note place="margin">Luk. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> who thanked God that he was not like
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16241:15"/>other men, for which he receiued no thanks of God; for he that truſteth in his owne heart is a foole, his truſt with himſelfe will ſuddenly decay.<note place="margin">Pro. 28.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Some put their truſt in their politick counſell, as Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophell, of whom it was ſaid, his counſell was reputed as an oracle of God.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.</note> But the Lord, ſaith Iob, catcheth the wiſe in their owne craftineſſe, and the counſell, of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked is made fooliſh.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Some put their truſt in their ſtrength (as Goliah did) in their ſword and ſhield, but curſed is he that maketh fleſh his arme.</p>
            <p>Some put their truſt in chariots, and ſome in horſes, but a horſe is a vaine thing to ſaue a man,<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.17.</note> neither ſhall he deliuer any by his great ſtrength <hi>Mentitur tibi equus quando promittit ſalutem,</hi> if thy horſe promiſe ſafety, he lieth vnto thee, ſaith Auguſtine.</p>
            <p>Proud Pharaoh that truſted to his horſes and chariots, found them lyars indeed; for when in the ſtrength of this conceit he had furniſhed himſelfe with ſix hundred cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, and was accompanied with all the Nobles, Captains, and ſouldiers, and ſo purſued the Iſraelites to the Red Sea: there their chariots and horſes failed them in which they truſted,<note place="margin">Exo. 14.</note> as hauing done ſeruice enough to bring their riders into perdition.</p>
            <p>What truſt now may be put in a horſe? The horſe is prepared for battell:<note place="margin">Pro. 21.31.</note> true, but the ſafely is of the Lord. Vaine is this truſt, for with Auguſt. <hi>mendax equus ad ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi> Woe to them that goe downe into Egypt for helpe, and comfort themſelues with chariots becauſe they are many, and with horſemen becauſe they are luſty and ſtrong,<note place="margin">Iſay 31.1.</note> but looke not to the holy One of Iſrael, nor ſeeke the Lord.</p>
            <p>Some put their truſt in Princes, and the ſonnes of men are their confidence, but Dauid biddeth vs not to put our truſt in Princes, nor in any child of man, for his breath goeth forth, and he returneth againe to his earth, and then all his thoughts periſh, Pſal. 146.3.</p>
            <p>See in theſe words the firſt and laſt, higheſt and loweſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16241:15"/>of the ſonnes of Adam, they may bee honorable becauſe Princes, but borne ſinfull the ſonnes of men, borne weake, for there is no helpe in them; borne mortall, their breath departeth; borne corruptible, for they returne to earth: and laſtly, their mortality is not onely in their fleſh, for their thoughts alſo periſh.</p>
            <p>The order of theſe words is ſo ſet that euery member is a reaſon or confirmation of that which went before. To this purpoſe that of <hi>Chyſoſtome</hi> is excellent, Truſt not in Princes, either becauſe they are men, or becauſe helpleſſe, or becauſe mortall, or becauſe corruptible in the frame of their bodies, in the cogitation of their hearts; or laſtly, <hi>Si dicendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt aliquid mirabile,</hi> if a man may ſpeake that which the world may iuſtly wonder at: truſt not in Princes euen for this cauſe, becauſe they are Princes, and in leaſt ſafety themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tamille timere cogitat qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>timeri,</hi> was <hi>Cyprians</hi> iudgement of one in gouernment, he hath as great cauſe to feare as to be feared. I read in <hi>Plutarch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Alexand.</note> that after <hi>Alexander</hi> the great had publiſhed that he was ſonne to <hi>Iupiter Hammon,</hi> yet when hee ſaw the humour running downe from his wounds was conſtrained to ſay, this is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the blood of man, not of God, and ſwelling the ſtench of his owne filth, asked his flatterers if the Gods yeeld ſuch a ſent.</p>
            <p>Where is <hi>Sapor</hi> King of Perſia,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marcelline. l.</hi> 17.</note> that tooke to himſelfe the proud title of King of Kings, brother to the Sunne and Moone, partaker of the Starres, like the proud Turker? Where is he? hath his pretended brother defended him? hath his pompe deliuered him from death?</p>
            <p>The like might I ſay of Herod, and of all the Potentates of the earth, yea of the Pope himſelfe, whoſe Canoniſts tell vs, that he is neyther God nor man: but we all know he is a man, and a man of ſinne, farre vnable to deliuer ſo many thouſands out of hell and his fayned purgatory, which can not deliuer himſelfe from treaſon, death and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Vaine fooles, which leaue God, and put their truſt in men, ſince the loweſt are vanity, the higheſt are vanity.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16241:16"/>The loweſt no leſſe, the higheſt no more. Surely man, ſaith Dauid, is altogether vanity.</p>
            <p>Some put their truſt in Diuels, as Saul when hee went to Endor, as all thoſe doe which runne in all ſickeneſſe and in all loſſes to wiſards, buzzards, ſorcerers, witches, diuels, for helpe and knowledge. Curſed be all thoſe that forſake the Lord, and runne to the Diuell for helpe.</p>
            <p>Some put their truſt in Angels and in Saints, imploring their ayde, and deſiring their helpe. But Iob ſayth, To which of the Saints wilt thou turn thee, meaning that none is able to helpe thee. Theſe therefore erre grieuouſly, and are giuen ouerto ſtrong deluſions, beleeuing a lie, in that they relie on the creature, and forſake the Creator, who is bleſſed for euer and euer.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thus for reproofe. Laſtly for obedience. You haue plainely now heard, that our helpe ſlandeth not in Angels, Saints or men, but onely in the name of the Lord, which hath made the heauen and the earth. Angels, Saints, Diuels, Men, Horſes. Chariots, Gold, Princes, not one or all theſe, nor any other externall meanes, can deliuer vs from any, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the leaſt iudgement which God ſhall lay vpon vs: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs not truſt in them: let vs take heed we enquire not of them, not relie vpon them. In whom then ſhall wee truſt? In the Lord Iehouah, and in his power alone.</p>
            <p>Let vs ſing that ſweet ſtrayne which the faithfull haue in the Prophet, <hi>Hicurruum &amp; illi equorum; nor vero nominis Dei Iehouae noſtri recordabimur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 20.7.</note> Let it bee the matter of our meditation in the day of trouble, &amp; in all rimes of diſtreſſe, let vs ſay in faith and ſure hope; Some truſt in chariots and ſome in horſes, but we will remember the name of the Lord our God. We will remember him and put our truſt in him alone.</p>
            <p>It we truſt in the Lord, a bleſſing ſhall attend vs. It is promiſed in Ieremy 17.7. Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in the Lord, and whoſe hope the Lord is. But how ſhall he be bleſſed? It followeth in the Propher, Hee ſhall bee as a tree planted by the waters, that ſpreadeth out her roots by the riuer whom the heat cannot hurt, whole leaues are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16241:16"/>greene: in a word, whatſoeuer he doeth, ſhall proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. And loe, thus ſhall the man be bleſſed that feareth and truſteth in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Let Alexander perſwade himſelfe to be the ſonne of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter Hamon till he ſee his bloud; let Sapor King of Perſia write himſelfe King of Kings, brother to the Sunne and Moone partner with the ſtarres. Let the Canoniſtes of Rome make a new Canon to transfigure their Pope into a new nature, making him to be neyther God nor man, but ſomewhat betweene both (I thinke a monſter.) Let Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus thinke to ſaile vpon the mountaynes. Let Senache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib thinke (like Xerxes hoſt) to drie vp the riuers with the plant of his foot. Let Edom exalt himſelfe like an Eagle, and build his neſt among the ſtarres, and in the clefts of the rocke, and ſay in the pride of his heart, who ſhall bring me downe to the ground? Let the couetous ſay to his gold, thou art my confidence, let the wicked vaniſh away in their mortall vanity: but let vs truſt in the Lord Iehouah, the mighty God of Iſrael, ſo ſhall wee euer finde mercy in time of need: which the ſame God grant for his Sonnes ſake, to whom with the holy Ghoſt be aſcribed all power and glory for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Text. And be doing good, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>FRom piety to pity is a iuſt conſequence; the gradation of the Prophet is excellent from ſure confidence to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy obedience, in which hee requireth that the inward and outward man may be both exerciſed. The former words ſtrooke at the heart, Truſt in the Lord, but theſe at the hand, at the outward conuerſation, and hee doing good, The ſtreames cannot chuſe but be wholeſome, if the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne be ſweet. For euen as the Sunne cannot bee without lire, the fire without heat, the body without a ſhadow, no more can ſayth and good workes be ſeparated; hence it is, that S. Iames challengeth an outward obedience, anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to an inward confidence; Shew mee thy fayth by thy works: thou ſayſt thou beleeueſt, ſhew it by thy doing good.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16241:17"/>
This beneficence which we ow to men by doing good, is not onely in this place glanced at, or barely repeated by the Prophet, but called for in many more places of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, as Heb. 13. To doe good forget not, and in many more places: and is expreſſed in the variety of no leſſe then foure epithites: 1. Doing good, 2. being rich in good workes, 3. ready to diſtribute, 4. willing to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n cate, diuers words all to one ſence; all is but beneficence, doing of good.</p>
               <p>This ingeminating (leſt any Atheiſt might quarrell at this waſte) is not any way ſuperfluous. The Scriptures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double the ſame wordes without fault of Tautologie; a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubling of the ſame ſence in diuers words without idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
                  <hi>Verbatoties incul. ata viua ſunt, vera ſunt, ſana ſunt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ſunt,</hi> as an ancient well ſayth. There is feruour in theſe repetitions, not looſeneſſe; God would haue our duty ſo plainely ſet downe, that hee that runneth may read it. As it was wont for this cauſe to be obſerued, both in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and acclamations to Princes, how oft the ſame word was reiterated, that by the frequence they might iudge of the vehemency of affection. It were eaſie to inſtance in many of this kinde, as eſpecially, Exod. 25.35. Pſa. 89.30. Ioh. 1.20. and in many more places.</p>
               <p>This heape of words therefore ſhewes the vehement in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of his deſire of good workes; whence I obſerue, That it is not left arbitrary to vs,<note place="margin">Doctr.</note> that wee may doe good if we will, but there is an important neceſſity of the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of good.<note place="margin">Illuſtr.</note> That it is layd vpon vs as our charge and duty, it is euident from hence in that it is poſitiuely by way of precept ſet downe, <hi>hoc fact,</hi> be doing good. The very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the expreſſion heereof in Timothy enforceth no leſſe: where it is ſayde, Charge the rich that they doe good, and be rich in doing good, in which place, as in this text, confidence in God and beneficence to men goe hand in hand together; neyther, as I ſpake, is it left as arbitrary to vs to doe or leaue vndone, but if wee ſayle in this latter, we are guilty of the former: For this is our charge and our duty; we muſt be doing good, and woe be to vs if wee doe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16241:17"/>not. This is nor a counſell, but a precept: although I might ſay of God, as we ſpeake of Princes, <hi>Sic volo, ſic iubeo, ſtat pro ratiom voluntas:</hi> his will is his command. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as you ſee them linked together and coupled in the text, I may iuſtly conclude the ſame neceſſity that there is of truſting in God, the ſame is in doing good to men.</p>
               <p>Hence it is, that the Apoſtle S. Iames ſo often calleth for deeds, <hi>Quid verba audiam, cumfacta videam?</hi> What auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Iacobs voyce, when we haue none other then Eſaus hands? Not the hearers but the doers of the law are iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And againe: See that yee bee doers of the word, and not hearers onely, deceiuing your owne ſelues: wherein the Apoſtle ſheweth, that God is better delighted with obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience then ſacrifice, with doings rather then ſayings: a leſſon fit for our time, wherein too many make perfuncto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hearing of Sermons, both duty and fruit of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; neuer doing any other good then hearing how to doe good; hauing a contemplatiue; but cold Chriſtianity in them, as if they did ow nothing but their cares vnto the Lord: whereas he who ſpeaketh by eare to the heart, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to the eare but for the heart, that we may heare with reuerence, and beleeue to obedience; and make them both perfect by our doing good.</p>
               <p>And not onely S. Iames is for doing good, but all the belles of Aaron and Chriſt ring the ſame peale. For Deut. 4.1. Hearken, O Iſrael, vnto the Lawes which I teach you to doe. Rom. 2.13: Not the hearers, but the doers, are righteous before God. Luke 11.28. Bleſſed are they that heare the word of God and keepe it. Ioh. 14.21. Hee that hath my commandements and keepeth them is he that loueth me. To which purpoſe S. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſpeaketh notablie:<note place="margin">Tract. <hi>75.</hi> in Ioan.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui habet in memoria &amp; ſeruat in vita; qui habet in ſermoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; ſeruat in moribus; qui habet audiendo &amp; ſeruat facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do; aut qui habet faciendo &amp; perſeuerando, ipſe eſt qui diligit me.</hi> He that hath my word in memory, and ſheweth it in his life; which hath it in mouth, and ſheweth it in his maners; that hath it in hearing, and ſheweth it in doing; that hath it in doing, and ſheweth it in perſeuering; this is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16241:18"/>he that loueth me. For as the ſame Father ſaith; <hi>Lex Dei te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur non audiendo ſed obediendo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eyiſt.</hi> 107.</note> 
                  <hi>non lectione, ſed dilectione.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So S. <hi>Hierome: Scripturarum cupimus verba in opera ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere, &amp; non dicere ſancta, ſed facere.</hi> So the reſt of that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſociety haue well obſerued, that Chriſtian Religion conſiſteth in practiſe, more then in theorie; being an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation, rather then a meere profeſſion, [of doing good.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>De virtute loqui minimum, virtutibus vti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>bor, hoc opus eſt,</hi> as <hi>Perſius</hi> ſpake, <hi>hoc Sampſonis opus eſt,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian.</hi> And not the worke of Sampſon, but alſo of Solomon; not onely of a ſtrong man, but in very deed of a wiſe man; euen as our Sauiour in the Goſpell ſheweth, ſaying; Whoſo heareth my words and doeth them, I will liken him to a wiſe man, which had built his houſe on a rocke, Matth.7.24.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, the Prophet Dauid ſheweth, what priuiledge belongeth to him that eſcheweth euill and doth good; in his Ep phonema or concluſion of the 15. Pſalme, Whoſo doth theſe things ſhall neuer fall. In which words, (as iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Caluin</hi> notes) the Prophet doth not ſay he that hears theſe things, or he that knowes theſe things, or he who can diſcourſe of theſe things; but he that doth theſe things: for as we iudge of the corporall health of the heart, not by the words of the mouth or colour of the countenance, but by the pulſe of the arme; ſo iudgement is made of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſoundneſſe of the heart, not ſo much by wordes and lookes as by the fruits of the hands. He ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen which doeth the will of my father which is in heauen, ſaith our Sauiour.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.21.</note> And if yee know theſe things, happy are ye if you doe them, Iohn 13.17. S. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De civit. Dei. l.6.6.2.</note> reporteth that <hi>Varro</hi> the great Philoſopher did read ſo much that it was admired how he could write any thing; againe he wrote ſo much that another could hardly read: now admit a man had as great knowledge in Diuinity as he in Philoſophie, that hee could ſpeake with the tongue of men and Angele and had not loue, whereby to doe good, he were as an <hi>inane nihil,</hi> ſounding braſſe, a tinckling cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball, 1. Cor. 13.1. Laſtly, the Apoſtle in the cited place tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16241:18"/>vs that faith muſt worke by loue, elſe it is no faith: So here our Prophet requireth the ſame. Firſt faith; truſt in the Lord. But let it worke by loue, in doing good. In which ſentence both the Prophet and the Apoſtle ſet forth the perfection of a Chriſtian in this life, which conſiſteth in 2. parts:
<list>
                     <item>Inwardly in ſayth to God,</item>
                     <item>Outwardly in doing good to men:</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Inwardly to God by faith, which needeth not our good workes. Pſal. 16.2. O God, my goodneſſe extendeth not to thee.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Outwardly to men by good workes; which neede not our faith, as it is written in the named place. But to the Saints that dwell vpon the earth. In which reſpect S. <hi>Aug. de ciuit. Dei, lib.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 1. ſayth, that doing of good, is <hi>pro ſacrificijs,</hi> accepted of God as a Sacrifice; Heb. 13.10. Yea, <hi>prae ſacrificijs,</hi> more then ſacrifice. Hoſea 6.6. I will haue mercy and not ſacrifice. For to be mercifull is the ſole work common to man with God, (as <hi>Syneſ.</hi>) nor indeed can we any way more neerely reſemble God, which is moſt good, then in our doing of good.<note place="margin">Greg.</note>
               </p>
               <p>To the neceſſary performance whereof in the next place, we are inuited by many, and thoſe moſt forcible reaſons: firſt:</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Becauſe in doing of good wee ſhall ſo ſhew our loue to God. So Chriſt teſtifieth in Iohn 14.16. If yee loue mee, keepe my commandements. Heerein our loue to God is made manifeſt, in walking as it becommeth his children. The compariſon is mod proper, if we marke it: for as in nature when children are neither in outward feature of the body, nor inward qualities of the minde, like to their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents which begat and brought them foorth, wee ſay, that ſuch children degenerate and grow out of kinde, neither can they be outwardly iudged to belong to their parents, by reaſon of that great diſſimilitude and vn likelines of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Euen ſo, on the contrary, when we ſee in the world men walking in by-paths of their own, and no way like to their heauenly father, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, no way reſembling him which hath begot them in Chriſt, in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16241:19"/>doing of good; we may (and iuſtly) ſay of ſuch, that they degenerate and grow out of kinde; they do not <hi>(patrizare)</hi> tread in their fathers ſteps, going about alwayes doing of good after the example of Chriſt Ieſus our elder brother.</p>
               <p>Againe, although we muſt walke, yet it is as children; and therefore weakly; yet notwithſtanding they ſhew their loue, in that they walke and follow ſo well as they can, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to goe on further if they could. And this is kindly accepted of a louing father. So is it with Almighty God, whoſe mercies are far greater, then our deſires or endeuors are or can be, who when hee ſeeth vs like louing children, following in the ſame way which he leadeth vs, accepteth our will for the deed, crowning his owne worke in vs.</p>
               <p>For although wee, as children, cannot tread in the ſame ſteps (as he ſpeaketh of <hi>Aſcanius</hi> in the Poet,)</p>
               <q>—ſequitur<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> patrem non paſſibus aequis.</q>
               <p>Yet we tread; and as we can goe along the very ſame way: and in this true and childlike reſemblance of him, wee ſhall much delight our holy father. This is the very argument which our Sauiour vſeth to the Iewes, Iohn 8.39. which ſtood much vpon their prerogatiues, <hi>nil niſi Cecropides,</hi> they boaſted themſelues to bee Abrahams ſeede, but hee telleth them that their boaſting was in vayne of their father, ſince they were ſo much degenerated from him, that they were no longer to bee accounted and called the children of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham. For when they tolde him Abraham is our father; Ieſus anſwered them, if yee were Abrahams children, yee would doe the workes of Abraham. For Abraham by his good workes glorified God, and ſhewed his loue to him in walking as his childe, ſo muſt all the true ſeed of Abraham be doing of good to ſhew their loue to God.</p>
               <p>Whereby moreouer God is glorified.] For like as when a childe, obſerueth in moſt dutifull maner, what his father commandeth, this redoundeth to the prayſe of the father; <hi>Omnet enim omnia bona dicere, &amp; laudare fortunas meas, qui fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium haberem tali ingenio praditum.</hi> So the Lord is glorified in his children, when they intend and ſeeke his honor and glory, by their obſeruing him in doing good, The coſtly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16241:19"/>rayment wherwith others are clothed, maketh to the praiſe of the worker; ſo it is ſayd of the good huſwife, giue her of the fruit of her hands, and let her workes prayſe her in the gates, Prou. 31.31. So the doing of good redoundeth vnto God, whoſe glory ought to be the end of our life and ſcope of all our actions, as Paul teacheth. Whether yee eate or drinke, or whatſoeuer ye doe, let all be done to the glory of God, 1. Cor. 10.30.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2. Becauſe in doing good we ſhall ſo ſhew our loues to our ſelues, and that in a two fold reſpect,
<list>
                     <item>1. in quieting our owne conſcience.</item>
                     <item>2. in making our election certayne.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>As touching the firſt, namely the peace of conſcience, S. Paul to Timothy 1.1.19. counſelleth him to hold faſt the fayth, and keepe a good conſcience; now indeed, what greater peace can be brought to the conſcience, then that, which ariſeth out of our doing of good through a liuelie fayth. And —</p>
               <p>As touching the ſecond, S. Peter carneſtly exhorteth, 2. Pet. 1.10. Giue diligence to make your calling and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſure: which cannot bee more effectually performed, then by our doing of good. This alone was the reioycing of the holy Apoſtle. What? Not that he had preached, not that hee had wrought miracles, or done extraordinary workes, but that in obedience to Gods commandements, and in ſincerity of heart, hee had his conuerſation in the world: So likewiſe his comfortable farewell to the world, is grounded vpon his fayth, which was ſhewed by loue, through both, concluding the peace of his conſcience, and the aſſurance of his election; I haue fought the good fight, I haue kept the fayth, I haue finiſhed my courſe, henceforth is laid vp for me a crowne of righteouſneſſe, 2. Tim. 4.7.</p>
               <p>Next vnto God what greater loue can be ſhewed then to our ſelues? But wherein can greater loue to our ſelues bee ſhewed, then in quieting of our conſciences, whereby our election may bee made ſure; This latter (as touching our ſelues) depending vpon the former, <hi>viz.</hi> the peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, this againe depending vpon our doing of good,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16241:20"/>which by more then a multitude of examples might bee ſhewed, what was that which quieted the conſcience, and ſealed the election of good Hezekiah, but onely this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable conſideration of his well doing? Remember, O Lord! how I haue walked before thee with an vpright heart, Eſay 38. And not onely Hezekiah, but all the children of God, in the middeſt of many fold temptations, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all conuulſions, haue beene ſo mainly ſuſtayned, that with Paul Rom. 14. they haue beene comfortably reſolued, and conſtantly aſſured; that whether we liue, we liue vnto the Lord; or whether we die, we die vnto the Lord: whether we liue therefore or die, we are the Lords.</p>
               <p>Except then wee endeauour our ſelues (by doing of good) we cannot haue a good conſcience, without a good conſcience and peace with it ſelfe, there is no peace to be had with God. Hence in a common popular apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a good conſcience is ſaid to be a ioyfull remembrance of a well-led life, ioyned with an hopefull expectation of a comfortable death, and a glorious reſurrection. In reſpect whereof it hath beene termed, the paradiſe of the ſoule, the iubile of the heart, <hi>laetitia cordis, quaſi latitia,</hi> a ſurpaſſing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſolace, ſo dilating and enlarging of the heart, for ſome good in poſſeſſion, more in expectation, that the ioy thereof can neither be ſuppreſſed nor expreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bona conſcientia</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) is <hi>titulus religionis, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum Solomonis, ager benedictionis, hortus deliciarum, gaudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um angelorum;</hi> A good conſcience is the title and crowne of religion, the temple of Solomon; the field of benediction, the garden of delight, the ioy of Angels, and Sanctuary of the holy Ghoſt, the tranquility of the minde, that heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muſick whereon the old Philoſophers doubtfully har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, but the good Chriſtians heart only heareth it, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twereth it with iuſt meaſures of ioy, which ſpirituall har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, as a ſong of three parts, conſiſteth in a throefold peace
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ſupra,</hi> with God aboue vs.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>extra,</hi> with men without vs.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>intra,</hi> and the ſoule within vs.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>O heauenly peace, whereby we are at league with God,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16241:20"/>with our neighbours, with our ſelues:</p>
               <p>O peace paſſing all vnderſtanding, which in reſpect of the minds tranquillity ioyned thereby, is like to the hidden Manna, and white ſtone wherein a name is written, which no man knoweth but he that enioyeth it.<note place="margin">Reu. 2, 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>O royall feaſt! farre excelling that of Ahaſueroſh, which laſted but nineſcore daies; for this is for eternity (whereat Angels are Cooks and Butlers, and the bleſſed Trinity gladſome gueſts (as <hi>Luther</hi> boldly ſpeakes) without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſolace, or interruption of ſocietie.</p>
               <p>A feaſt in life, refreſhing the ſoule with daitnty cates of diuine comfort.</p>
               <p>A feaſt in ſickneſſe, when worldly hopes hang downe their head like a bulruſh.</p>
               <p>A feaſt in death, when world and worldly comforts and comforters forſake vs.</p>
               <p>A feaſt in the reſurrection, and after that a feaſt for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
               <p>If then this be not a ſufficient motiue and reaſon to mooue vs to the doing of good, let me ſhew you another.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Becauſe in doing good, we ſhall ſo ſhew our loue to our neighbours, and that in a twofold reſpect,
<list>
                     <item>1 to witneſſe our faith vnto them.</item>
                     <item>2 to winne them to Chriſt.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>That we ſhall thus make a reall manifeſtation of our faith Saint Iames ſheweth, when he ſaith, Shew me thy faith by thy works, Iames 2.18. Faith if it haue not works is dead, being alone. Yea a man may ſay thou haſt faith and I haue works: ſhew me thy faith without thy works and I will ſhew thee my faith by my works. And againe, With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works faith is dead. And, as the body without the ſpirit is dead, ſo faith without works is dead alſo, verſ laſt.</p>
               <p>Man can iudge no further then hee hath warrant from outward appearance, although God doth iudge the heart: it is neceſſary therefore, that of a good tree there be alſo ſome good fruits. So Chriſt, either make the tree good and the fruit good, or the tree euill and the fruit euill; and that we ſhould witneſſe our faith to men, our Sauiour moſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16241:21"/>plainely ſheweth, where he ſaith, Le before men, that they may ſee your good works.</p>
               <p>And that thereby they may bee wonne [and ſo glorifie your Father which is in heauen. To this purpoſe is that of the Apoſtle S. Paul, 1. Cor. 7.14. The vnbeleeuing huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band is ſanctified by the wife; and the vnbeleeuing wife by the husband: elſe were your children vncleane, but now they are holy. And in the 16. verſe. For what knoweſt thou, ô man, whether thou ſhalt ſaue thy wife, or what knoweſt thou, ô wife, whether thou ſhalt ſaue thy husband? As if he had ſayd, Thou maieſt by thy holy life and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation be a meanes to winne, him or her, to Chriſt. Euen as the barke of the tree is a beauty or ornament, and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a couer to it; ſo (for men are likened to trees) a good conuerſation is an ornament to a Chriſtian, <hi>&amp; corpus te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens, &amp; cor protegens:</hi> decking the ſoule inwardly, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting the body outwardly, and moouing good reſpect to both. A good outſide (though not alwaies) argues a good inſide; a good conuerſation a ſigne of ſanctification. Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and holy maners, are compared to precious treaſures which are commodious to our ſelues and others. To our ſelues, <hi>ad iuſtificandum,</hi> but not effectiuely, for ſo we are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by Chriſt. But not apprehenſiuely, for ſo wee are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by fayth. But yet declaratiuely, by iuſt and holy workes. So our Sauior of himſelfe. The works that I haue done, beare witneſſe what I am.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To others, <hi>ad adificandum,</hi> that they ſeeing our good workes may glorifie our father which is in heauen; and ſo be wonne by our godlie life and conuerſation. For, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur exemplis:</hi> man is led by practiſe more then inſtruction, like pliable wax for any impreſſion. Nothing more forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and perſwaſiue with the vulgar then examples, which are as looking glaſſes to the eies of men. <hi>Validiora ſunt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empla quam verba,</hi> as <hi>Bernard.</hi> A good man (ſaith a good Father) <hi>&amp; carbo &amp; lampas eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Grag. in Ezech. bom. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> he is a coale burning, and a lampe ſhining, <hi>&amp; ſibi ardet &amp; alijs lucet;</hi> He doth warme his owne conſcience and heats himſelfe well, and ſheweth a good light vnto others alſo. Euen as by the buſh wee iudge
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16241:21"/>that there is wine, ſo men iudge of our hearts by the outward countenance, and God of our workes by the inward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. For, <hi>Sermo interpres cordis apud virum, cor interpres ſermouis apud Deum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Philo Iudaeus:</hi> Men according to our outward parts, but God according to our inward hearts. Paul for this cauſe exhorteth thoſe which profeſſe Chriſt to haue their conuerſation honeſt and harmeleſſe, that the name of God may not be blaſphemed among the Gentiles: and not only ſo, but that they may winne thoſe that are without by their holy cariage and conuerſation, according to that of the Prophet Iſaiab, 61.9. Their ſeed ſhalbe known among the Gentiles, and their of spring among the people. All that ſee them ſhall acknowledge them, that they are the ſeed that the Lord hath bleſſed. And if this reaſon bee not ſufficient, let me lead you yet further.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> Becauſe this is the commandement of God, to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance whereof we are inuited <hi>&amp;</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>à praemio,</hi> from the reward.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>à periculo,</hi> from the danger.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>That God commands it without further reaſon why, is ſufficient reaſon for vs to do it. And that it is the command of the higheſt, it appeareth in many places. Eſchew euill, and doe good. To doe good, forget not. <hi>Date eleemoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</hi> Luke 11.41. Charge the rich that they bee fruitfull in good workes; and heere be doing good. And in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places which command implies obedience, if we go no further then the command it ſelfe; for he that commanded it to be done is that mighty one, high aboue all men and angels, by whoſe command all things were made; for <hi>dixit &amp; factuns eſt,</hi> but that the Lord might leaue vs inexcuſable, and that euery mouth might be ſtopped, he hath enforced the ſame by a double reaſon. For, <hi>hoofac &amp; vines:</hi> do this<note place="margin">A praemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and thou ſhalt liue. There is a reward greater then our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. Againe, he that looketh in the perfect law of liberty, and continueth therein, being not a forgetfull hearer, but a doer of the worke, the ſame ſhall bee happie in his deed: which happineſſe is no leſſe then eternall life; then which, what reward can be greater? Againe, wee are exhorted by
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16241:22"/>good workes on earth, to lay vp for our ſelues treaſures in heauen; to bring ſomewhat into Gods exchequer, as the Iſraelites to the Tabernacle, whereof (in ſingular confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, clayming an eſpeciall intereſt in Gods fauour, and expecting the promiſed recompence) we may ſay with Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah, Remember me, O God, concerning this.</p>
               <p>For albeit the glory of God bee the <hi>vltimus terminus</hi> of our cogitations, actions, well doing, and principall motiue of our good workes; and as it were the <hi>primum mobile</hi> of our obedience, yet (as <hi>Aquinas</hi>) in the actions of our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whileſt we ſeeke the aduancement of Gods glory in the firſt place, we may as a ſecondary obiect or adiunct re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect our owne commodity, and haue an eie to our owne reward; for ſhall Iob, or any one, ſerue God for nothing?</p>
               <p>But as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, in Pal. 100. <hi>Niſi Deus per mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordiam parceret, non inueniret quos per iuſtitiam corenaret:</hi> Except God ſhould ſpare in mercy, he ſhould finde none to crowne in iuſtice. For as conſcious to our ſelues of our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny imperfections in our beſt actions, of defects and faults in the end, matter, maner, or meaſure of our obedience, we muſt ſupplicate and ſay, <hi>miſericordia tua meritum meum,</hi> thy mercie is my merie, pardon me according to thy great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. In hope and expectation of which infinite reward, we muſt in our ſeuerall callings, dailie be doing good, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our ſelues in works of piety and pity, that ſo our ſoules as fields of ſincerity, being daily more and more charged with the deeds of mercy, we may at length be accompliſht with the ereſt and crowne of eternall glory, as himſelfe hath promiſed, Matt. 5. Bleſſed be the mercifull for they ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine mercy.<note place="margin">Luk. 6.35. Iohn. 14.1.</note> They ſhall be called the children of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; and therefore haue a dwelling place in their fathers houſe. For, <hi>Quimiſeretur proximo, ſoeneratur domino,</hi> he that caſts his bread vpon the waters, ſhall after many daies find for a crumme a crowne, for one mite a million, for a drop of cold water, a full draught of that heauenly water, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hauing taſted, he ſhall neuer thirſt any more; and in a word, for the gleanings and refuſe of our vintage, a ful mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure preſſed and running ouer; ſaithfull is he that promiſed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16241:22"/>to performe it.</p>
               <p>But if we cannot be wonne by reward, let vs be wreſted by danger for feare of puniſhment; for feare and anguiſh ſhall be vpon euery ſoule that doeth euill, and take and bind that vnprofitable ſeruant, and caſt him into vtter darkneſſe, there ſhall be weeping, and wailing and gnaſhing of teeth: this is their portion for euer: <hi>ignorans ignorabitur;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Primoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Aquin.</note> hee that will not know God by doing good, ſhall not be known of God, among thoſe to whom he ſhall ſhew himſelfe good.</p>
               <p>Theſe forenamed reaſons; firſt to ſhew our loue to God in walking as his children: ſecondly, to ſhew our loue to our ſelues,
<list>
                     <item>In quieting our conſciences,</item>
                     <item>In making our election ſure.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, to ſhew our loue to our neighbours,
<list>
                     <item>In witneſſing our faith,</item>
                     <item>In winning them by our godly conuerſation.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, in yeelding obedience to the commandement of God,
<list>
                     <item>In reſpect of the reward,</item>
                     <item>In reſpect of the danger.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe reaſons, I ſay, (as a cord diuinely twiſted) are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently able to moue vs to, and to confirm vs in the doing of good.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Firſt then, let vs ſling this ſtone into the brazen fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads of our Aduerſaries, which in their ſhameſſe chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of our Religion, dare tell the world, that we are all for faith, nothing for good workes: all for ſaying, but nothing for doing. And that we hold workes to ſaluation, as a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentheſis to a clauſe, that it may bee perfect without them. Heauen and earth ſhall witneſſe the iniuſtice of this calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niation, and the conſciences of all which heare vs, ſhall bee our compurgators, which teſtifie, that there is no leſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of doing good workes, then if you ſhould bee ſaued by them; and th t though you cannot be ſaued by them, as the meritorious cauſe of your glory, yet that you cannot be ſaued without them, as the neceſſary effects of that grace which brings glory. We ſay and maintaine, that <hi>fides nuda,</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:16241:23"/>is <hi>fides nulla;</hi> a naked faith, is no true fayth; to the conuicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that lewd ſlander of Solifidianiſme. For although we doe not, wee dare not, make inherent righteouſneſſe the cauſe of our iuſtification, yet wee ſay it is the effect thereof, though with the Papiſts we make it not the Vſher, yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Parent of iuſtification, yet we require it as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, at leaſt the Page thereof.</p>
               <p>But ſome man may ſay, what matters it, if both aſcribe the whole worke to God For comes it not all to one, if one pay a ſumme for me or giue it me to pay my ſelfe?</p>
               <p>Theſe things may ſeeme little diſſonant to ſome mens cares, yet the ſpirit of God hath made them vtterly incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible. For it is written, To him that worketh the wages is not imputed of grace, but of debt, if by grace, now not of works, for elſe grace ſhould be no more grace, Rom. 4.4. Epheſ. 2.8. for neither is it grace any way if it bee not free euery way, ſaith Aug. But they ſay, therefore of grace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of works. Not of works, leſt any man ſhould boaſt, ſaith the ſpirit. But of workes, and yet a man ſhall boaſt in the Lord, ſaith <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> This may ſeeme to ſound well to an ignorant eare, to ſay (God hath giuen this to me whereby I am iuſt) but well conſidered, vnder pretence of piety ſpoiles Chriſt of his glory. Why doth not the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt as well ſay, he hath giuen me wherewith to redeeme my ſelfe? for by the ſame wherewith we are iuſtified, wee are redeemed: as it is written — <hi>being iuſtified by his blood</hi>) Rom. 5.9 Behold the blood of him that is God and man iuſtifies vs, and that redeemes vs, for in vaine had Chriſt died for vs, if by meat and drinke we our ſelues might haue purchaſed the Kingdome of God. But the matter is farre otherwiſe, for, all, ſaith S. Auguſt. which are iuſtified by Chriſt, are iuſt, not in themſelues, but in him. That which is Chriſts, becauſe it is his, is moſt perfect; that which is ours, becauſe ours, is weake and vnperfect. Iuſtly doth <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> deride <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſiphon</hi> in the like caſe, as we may theſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit-mongers. O bleſſed, O happy men, if that iuſtice, which can be found no where but in heauen, may be found with you only vpon earth. Therefore let them boaſt of their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16241:23"/>good works, of arrogance and ſuperarrogance, let vs in humility take vp that notable ſpeech of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> I will not boaſt becauſe I am iuſt, but becauſe I am redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: I will not boaſt becauſe I am voyd of ſinne, but that my ſinnes are forgiuen. Contrary boaſting, for that wee haue, nor can finde iuſt cauſe in our ſelues, nor warrant from the word, we ſhall leaue to <hi>Enagrius, Priſcillian, Iovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> the <hi>Meſſalians, Pelagians,</hi> and the reſt of that rout, which magnifying their own fooliſh fancies, make the word of God of none effect. The humble confeſſion of the poore publican liketh vs well, O Lord bee mercifull vnto me a ſinner.</p>
               <p>But for the further opening of the difference betweene the Papiſts and vs, and for the more full cleering of our ſelues, from their falſe accuſation of vs; you ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that the Rhemiſts haue gathered two princip all concluſions againſt vs; both out of theſe words of Paul, <hi>If I haue all faith, ſo that I can remoue mountaines, and haue not charity, I am nothing,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, that, True faith may bee without loue, works.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, that, Faith alone doth not iuſtifie, without good works.</p>
               <p>To the firſt, we anſwere them; that ſpeech of Paul is nota categoricall propoſition, but an hypotheticall ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; as, if it were poſſible that faith could bee without workes, it were nothing.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the faith which Saint Paul here ſpeaketh of, is not a iuſtifyng or a ſauing faith, but a miraculous faith; of which our Sauiour in the Goſpell, If yee had faith, as much as a graine of muſtard feed, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This he ſpake to the beleeuing Apoſtles, and therefore cannot be vnderſtood of a ſauing faith, as alſo S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> interpreteth that Text, to doe wonders, and to caſt out Deuils by faith, is nothing worth, except a man be a fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of God, by good conueſation; thus he, thus we.</p>
               <p>There is a dead faith, Iam. 2.20.</p>
               <p>There is a liuely faith, Gal. 2.20.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:16241:24"/>
There is a faith of Deuils, Iam. 2.19.</p>
               <p>There is a faith of Gods elect, Tit. 1.1.</p>
               <p>There is an enduring faith, Iohn 3.15.</p>
               <p>There is a periſhing faith, Luke 8.13.</p>
               <p>There is a faith which the world deſtroyeth, 2 Tim. 2.18.</p>
               <p>There is a faith which deſtroyeth the world, I Iohn 5.4.</p>
               <p>There is a faith whereby we beleeue a God, Iam. 2.19.</p>
               <p>There is a faith whereby we beleeue in God, Ioh. 14.1.</p>
               <p>According to the differences of faith in ſcripture, there is a faith without workes, and a faith with workes; hence Diuines haue a fourefold conſideration of faith, as it is
<list>
                     <item>hiſtoricall. miraculous,</item>
                     <item>temporarie, iuſtifying.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Three of which kinds, may be in the reprobate; but that other iuſtifying faith can be in none but Gods eiect; whereby we doe not only beleeue a God, nor beleeue God only,<note place="margin">Credere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Deo, Deum, in Deum.</note> but beleeue in God; to which the promiſe of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation &amp; of ſaluation is made; &amp; of this faith once &amp; againe (if they will heare vs) we ſay; it cannot be ſeparated from charity, but whereſoeuer it is it bringeth forth good works, to the praiſe and glory of God: of this in S. <hi>Auguſt</hi> words we conclude, <hi>Inſeparabilis eſt bona vita à fide, quaper dilecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem operatur, imo verò ea ipſa eſt bona vita;</hi> in his booke <hi>de fide &amp; operibus.</hi> Whereunto accordeth <hi>Irenaus lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. to beleeue is to Doe as God will.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond concluſion, <hi>viz.</hi> That faith alone iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not. We anſwere. Although faith be not <hi>ſolitaria,</hi> yet in our iuſtification it is <hi>ſola:</hi> A worthy Diuine of ours hath a worthy ſaying to this purpoſe, Euen as the eye, in regard of being, is neuer alone from the head, yet in reſpect of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it is alone, for it is the eye only that doth ſee: So faith ſubſiſteth not without other graces of God, as hope, loue, &amp;c. yet in regard of the act of iuſtification it is alone, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all, conſidered by it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>To make this plaine, we muſt know that the ſeparating of things is or
<list>
                     <item>reall, <hi>in ſubiecto,</hi> the ſubiect.</item>
                     <item>mentall, <hi>in anime,</hi> the vnderſtanding:</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:16241:24"/>
The firſt reall ſeparation of faith and charity wee really, wholly deny: and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> honeſtly eleereth <hi>Luther, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthou, Chemnitius, Calvin,</hi> and other learned Proteſtants herein; who (he confeſſeth) teach good works to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſaluation, <hi>de iuſtificat. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. §. <hi>ac primum confeſſio, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond: mentall ſeparation, which
<list>
                     <item>Is negatiue; when in the vnderſtanding one thing is denied, another affirmed.</item>
                     <item>Is priuatiue; when of things that cannot bee parted, yet a man vnderſtands one, and omits the other.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> Light and heat cannot be ſeparated in fire, yet a man may conſider the light, and not the heat. Briefly, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiuely, we doe not ſeparate good works from fayth; but priuatiuely we make them not concurring cauſes, but ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and conſequents, of our iuſtification: our aſſertion then, faith conſidered, without good workes doth iuſtifie. <hi>Operaſunt via non cauſa regnandi</hi> (ſayth <hi>Bernard;</hi>) and with <hi>Aug. Opera non pracedunt iuſtificandum, ſed ſequuntur iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum:</hi> not goe before, but after iuſtification. Euen (as our Church ſpeaketh) the wheele turneth round,<note place="margin">Homily of good works.</note> nor to the end to be made round, but becauſe it is firſt made round, therefore it turneth round; ſo men are ſanctified, becauſe firſt iuſtified, not iuſtified, becauſe firſt ſanctified: neither is this concluſion ours, alone, but the Fathers, and the Reformed Churches; yea of ſome of the Papiſts, and thoſe alſo of the greateſt Clerks among them: as it may appeare, <hi>viz.</hi> If we caſt our eies backe to the ancient Doctors, they are all for vs in this point; Not according to the worth of our workes, ſaith <hi>Baſil,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; to beleeue onely, ſaith <hi>Nazianzene.</hi> Faith alone is ſufficient, ſaith <hi>Hierom.</hi> By beleeuing, men are iuſtified, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> and with theſe conſort the reſt, <hi>Epiphanius, Chryſoſtome, Primaſius,</hi> and the whole ſacred quire of Antiquity; although yet wee are not ignorant, that the Expurgatory Index of Spaine, hath purpoſelywip't out of <hi>Chryſoſtome, Hierom</hi> and <hi>Cyril,</hi> moſt cleare teſtimonies for iuſtification by fayth. But (as <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:16241:25"/>to the Arrians) they haue blot out the letters, but the fayth cannot be aboliſht; thoſe blots condemne them more then the writing.</p>
               <p>Next, the Reformed Churches ſpeake the ſame thing: ſo, the Church of England. <hi>art.</hi> 12. the Church of Saxony <hi>tit. de mona obedientia,</hi> the Confeſſion exhibited to Charles the Fifth, and explaned at <hi>Wormes, anno</hi> 1540. <hi>Luther com. ad Galat. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Melancthon loc. com.</hi> and <hi>Catechiſ. Iewe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Apolog. Caluin. in Inſtit. Chenonitius in Examinat. Trident. Conc. Zanchius;</hi> and all others in their Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, that their owne Rabbies, haue ſo taught, is eaſie to ſhew. <hi>Caſſander (conſultat. de iuſtificat.)</hi> ſayth; That which is affirmed, that men cannot be iuſtified before God, by their ſtrength, merit or workes; but that they are freely iuſtified by fayth, was alwayes allowed, and receiued in the Church of God; and is at this day approued, by all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall writers.</p>
               <p>The great Doctor of the Schooles <hi>The. Aquinas, in Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. &amp; Iacob.</hi> 2 attributes iuſtification to works, not as iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification is taken for an infuſion of grace; but as it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for an exerciſe, manifeſtation, and conſummation of iuſtice. So <hi>Caietan in Comment. in Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>Behold the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, behold the righteouſneſſe, whoſe wages is eternall life, but to vs in reſpect of Ieſus Chriſt, it is a free gift:</hi> What could either <hi>Luther,</hi> or <hi>Calvin,</hi> or any Proteſtant ſpeake more plainly?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>Arias Montanus</hi> (a learned author, how euer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his time faulty in opinion in many things)—It followes (ſaith he) that faith is imputed for righteouſneſſe, to him that works not in the law, and that according to the purpoſe of the grace of God: It is therefore a true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that faith alone iuſtifieth, as hath beene proued.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, a loud lie, a lewd ſlander, (<hi>Bellarmine</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being witneſſe) that our Goſpell is carnall, and the high way to Epicuriſme: So that we ſay (with <hi>Auguſt.</hi>) <hi>nemo legem ita intelligis, ſed qui non intelligit:</hi> no man ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth the doctrine of our Church, but he that wants
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16241:25"/>vnderſtanding: We ſay that good works muſt make faith fat: and without holineſſe no man ſhall ſee God:<note place="margin">Luther.</note> but as for meritorious butchering of Kings, vncleane chaſtity, drunken faſts, vncharitable charity, ſelling of heauen to the rich, and ſending the poore to purgatory for want of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; we are content if they will that they appropriate theſe to themſelues: We deſire to be iuſtified by faith, without any conſideration had (in the very matter) to good works: yet in all duties of religion, and honeſty; dare iuſtifie our ſelues (in compariſon of them) vnto the whole world, though hereby, we doe not iuſtifie our ſelues before God: and will euermore labour to expreſſe our true faith of tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in God, by the deeds of mercy, in doing of good.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> A ſecond vſe hereof teacheth all men, thoſe whom God hath ioyned together, no man may put aſunder, except withall he ſeuer himſelfe from God: a liuely faith muſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be accompanied with good works, theſe two like our armes, muſt embrace each other, or like the two Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims, muſt ioyntly looke to one mercy ſeat, which is Chriſt.</p>
               <p>We read in Nehemiah, that the children of Iſrael, being hindred from the reedifiing of Hieruſalem by Sanballet the Horonite, and by Tobiah the Ammonite; laboured in the worke, holding a ſword in the one hand, and a Trowell in the other: So muſt all Gods Iſraell doe, for that they haue many Horonites, and Ammonites, bodily and ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſers of them, they muſt hold the ſword of faith faſt in the one hand, wherewith, if need require they may bee able to reſiſt all gainſayers, and quit themſelues like men: and a Trowell in the other, wherewith they may build; laying vpon the foundation of faith, the faire and comely buildings of good works, that their light may bee ſeene by the good works of their hands, and God which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen may be glorified.</p>
               <p>Thy Commandement O Lord (ſaith Dauid) is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding broad; ſo is this Commandement of Doing good; for (as all learned Interpreters obſerue) this precept of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, comprehendeth, and containeth in it, all duties
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16241:26"/>of the firſt table, concerning piety toward God, and all the reſt of the duties of the ſecond table, touching charity toward our neighbours; Neither is it any way a needleſſe obſeruation, or vnprofitable: that the works of the ſecond table, doe not only concerne our neighbors: for although outwardly they be done to men, and immediately as the proper obiect of them; yet indeed they are done alſo to God, and he is ſaid more to delight in them, then in all burnt ſacrifice: for if wee feed our brethren, cloath the naked, viſit the ſicke, or any way be Doing good, God ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth theſe things as done to himſelſe. Hence it is that when any preſcription is made in Scripture, to men, what they muſt doe, vſually the workes of the ſecond table are appointed: not that they are better, or to bee preferred before the works of the firſt table, but for that they are the true bewrayers of them: for euery hypocrite will ſay hee loueth God, feareth God, truſteth in God, and the like: becauſe theſe are ſecret duties in the heart, and of man cannot be iudged: but looke how he liueth toward men, and it may be ſoone ſeene, that failing in the duties of the ſecond table towards men; the duties of the firſt table, which he boaſteth of, in truth are not in him: for if they were, they would bring forth the other, as it written, Hee that ſaith he loueth God whom he neuer ſaw, and hateth his brother whom he hath ſeene, is a lyer, 1 Iohn. 4.</p>
               <p>This alſo (as ſome obſerue) occaſioned that queſtion of the Prophet, Pſal. 15.1. Lord who ſhall dwell in thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle? or who ſhall reſt vpon thy holy hill? to which queſtion the Lord maketh this anſwere: hee that leadeth an vncorrupt life: plainely to be ſeene in his eſchewing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and Doing good, as it followeth at large in that place:</p>
               <p>All are not Iſrael that are of Iſrael; all that liue within the pale of the viſible Church, are not of the Church. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> vpon that place: <hi>mult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſunt corporae quinon ſunt ſide.</hi> And of <hi>Turrecrematus, mult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſunt nomine qui non ſunt numine:</hi> many are ſhuffled among corne, lewes outwardly, but not inwardly, deceiuing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16241:26"/>often, and moſt of all, and worſt of all, themſelues, with a bare profeſſion of Religion, and an opinion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the practiſe of piety. But we (beloued) are to know, that the dwelling in the Tabernacle of the Church, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing of the word, frequenting the place of worſhip, the ſaying Lord, Lord, a bare externall profeſſion of our faith, and outward Communion with the Church, is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vnto ſaluation, except wee lead an vncorrupt life, correſpondent to the ſame, doing that which is right and good, and ſpeaking truth from our heart.</p>
               <p>It is not ſufficient to rely vpon the Churches outſide (as the Papiſts doe) vpon the ſucceſſion of Roman Biſhops, vpon the multitude of Roman Catholicks, vpon the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and pompe of the Roman Synagogue, crying with the Iewes of old: <hi>templum Domini,</hi> the temple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord.</p>
               <p>It is not enough, with the carnall and careleſſe Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; to place all Religion in the formall obſeruation of all outward ſeruice and ceremonies: for a verball Chriſtian only, is a reall Atheiſt: according to that of S. Paul: In word they profeſſe to know God, but in their workes they denie him: we muſt take heed, that wee bee not Chriſtians in lip, and not in life; making (as holy Martyr Bradſord ſayd) a maske of Religion, or rather a very vizard, with eyes and mouth, and noſe, fairely painted, and proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to all pretences and purpoſes: but if we be indeed the children of God, we muſt in true ſincerity of heart, be Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of good. The Kings daughter is all glorious within, and alſo without: within, as hauing a cleere conſcience, and truth in the inward affections, a cleane heart and a new ſpirit: without, as hauing on for a garment, a veſture of gold, wrought about with diuers colours: ſhee is cloathed with righteouſnes, as with a garment, and hath it wrought moſt gloriouſly, with the deeds of mercy, which as a chec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker worke, of diuers colours, embroidered with the pure ſilken twiſt of a helpfull and vpright conuerſation, garniſh her holy profeſſion. The Doing of good, is the certificate of a Chriſtian, the character of a mans faith, making his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16241:27"/>and election ſure. And</p>
               <p>Although it may be obiected, that a hypocrite may ſeem iuſt in Doing good; and yet bee abominable before God; not doing that which is good, for righteouſneſſe ſake, <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto pius &amp; ſceleratus co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em</hi> (as the Poet pithily ſpake) Wee behold the man, not the minde; the worke, not the will; the fact, not the faith; the action, not the end; yet the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of charity, belongs properly to men; but the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of certainty to God. From whence wee muſt labour in our wel doing, not ſo much to approue our ſelues to men, as to God, who ſeeth our hearts.</p>
               <p>And that we may not be negligent nor flouthfull heerin, and thinke that becauſe our workes iuſtifie vs not, and God ſeeth wee loue him well, although wee doe little good on earth; to encourage vs to well doing on the one ſide, and to preuent ſuch conceits on the other; the holy Ghoſt in Pſa. 24.3 4. in Eſay 33 15. in Pſa. 15. and many places, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes a ſound member of the Church, rather by workes then faith, and of all the fruits of fayth, almoſt innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, make choice of thoſe that concerne our neighbour: in all which, ſaith is yet preſuppoſed; according to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall axiome, whatſoeuer is not of ſaith is ſinne: <hi>fides eſt operum fomes</hi> (as <hi>Paulinus</hi> ſpake,) and (as our Church) the neſt of good workes: for bee our birds neuer ſo fayre, and our leaues neuer ſo freſh and greene, all are but loſt, if they be not brought forth in a true beleefe: for admit a man were as iuſt as Ariſtides in his gouernment; as true of his word as Pomponius; as louing and kinde to his countrey as Curtius at Rome, Mecaenas at Thebes, Codrus at Athens, who expoſed themſelues to voluntary death, for their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and countries ſake; yet if theſe workes proceed not from a heart purged by faith, no happineſſe can follow this Doing of good, no true peace to the conſcience, nor eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reſt to the ſoule; for without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</p>
               <p>Yet, when theſe are conceiued and brought forth in faith, the Lord (as it is ſayd of Abel and his offring) hath reſpect, to both the worke it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Gen.4.4.</note> and him that wrought it; and (as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16241:27"/>it is ſaid of Noahs ſacrifice) the Lord ſmelleth a ſweet ſauor of reſt, and is well pleaſed with them.<note place="margin">Gen. 8.2.</note> Heb. 13.16. A man may deceiue himſelfe and others, with a fained profeſſion of faith, an inward and hidden grace: therefore the holy ſpirit will haue euery mans fayth to be tried and known by his fruits; By their fruites yee ſhall know them. Doe men gather grapes of thornes, or figges of thiſtles? And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer eternall life be promiſed to ſayth, and eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation be threatned to infidelity, yet the ſentence of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and of damnation ſhall be pronounced according to workes, as the cleareſt euidence of both, Matt. 25.34. but with the Apoſtle; I will ſhew you yet a more excellent way.</p>
               <p>This precept then of Doing good, is of large extent, in that it concerneth all duties, and all degrees of men, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in common, as we are men, and ſo bound vnto that <hi>ius gentium</hi> to render euery man his due; but in particular, in our ſeuerall vocations and callings, to expreſſe our fayth by Doing of good; as wee are Magiſtrates or Miniſters, Maſters or Seruants, in what eſtate, degree or condition of life it hath pleaſed God to place vs.</p>
               <p>For, know ye all, that not onely thoſe generall duties of Chriſtianity, as the hearing of the word &amp;c. are required; wherein, if we fayle, all the world can witneſſe againſt vs, and euery one <hi>(quaſi digito)</hi> will point at vs, and crie open ſhame of vs: not onely theſe (I ſay) are carefully to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; but moreouer, the particular offices, whereunto we are called, for the propagation of Religion and piety; or the preſeruation of order, iuſtice, and equity in the Church or Common wealth, and our priuate familie are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to be attended and executed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hoc agire,</hi> in the ſacrifice of the heathen gods, was a precept much vſed and obſerued; how much more in the ſeruices of the God of heauen, ſhould the ſaid precept (Doe yee this, that is, intend, and apply all the faculties of your minde, to the doing of it) be kept inviolable?</p>
               <p>What other thing, doth the Apoſtle inſinuate? when he ſaith. He endeauored, to haue alwaies a cleere conſcience
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16241:28"/>toward God and men, but this point in hand; That there ought to be a concurrence of our holy carriage towards God, and vpright demeanor towards men. Requiſite it is ſaith <hi>Chry.</hi>) <hi>ut rovere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter ſe quis habeat ad divina, &amp; landabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſetur cum hominib.</hi> that euery good Chriſtian ſhould ſerue God reuerently with hearty deuotion, and man righteouſly with a ready minde, and a liberall diſpoſition. Men are to be regarded in the way of right and equity, <hi>propter famam;</hi> God is to be reuerenced in the way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and piety, <hi>propter conſcientiam:</hi> Holineſſe and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe are the meane parts of Gods image in man, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. 4. Neither can wee be aſſurd that we are regenerated, vnleſſe we finde in our ſelues a marriage of them both.</p>
               <p>To what end hath the grace of Soluation appeared? if not to this end; to teach vs to liue godly, in reſpect of our great and glorious maker and maſter: to liue ſoberly, in reſpect of our ſelues: to liue iuſtly, in reſpect of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: if we haue with the ouerweening Phariſee, great godlineſſe in our philacteries, fringes, and care-ſeruice, frequenting the Lectures of the Law, not caring how wee liue; we ſhall ſeeme holy without righteouſneſſe: and if with the ſimple ſeduced Saduces, we liue honeſtly, and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilly, but beleeue nor Angels, ſpirits, nor reſurrection, wee ſhall appeare righteous without holineſſe: either of theſe commeth ſhort of that obedience which is required of God, who will not be ſerued with holineſſe only, nor righteouſneſſe only, but with both. Againe, to what end hath the Lord giuen vnto euery one a ſeuerall gift, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in this preſent world? if not for this end, to employ them in Doing of good, in our ſeuerall places, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his name, and good of his Church. This matter then of Doing good, concerning vs all, is to be conſidered of vs all in particular.</p>
               <p>Particularly, the Magiſtrate muſt bee carefull to Doe good. Vp and be Doing of good you Magiſtrates; exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe your talents; a great meaſure of well-doing is expected from you, God and man call daily for it, and you ſhall well performe it, if you will riſe betimes (with Dauid) and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16241:28"/>puniſh the workers of iniquity, if in the zeale of Phineas, you will execute iudgement in Iſrael, if you will for the better examples ſake, ſanctifie the Lords Sabbath your ſelues, and command the ſanctification of the ſame by others, if you will countenance the good, defend the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe, take the cauſe of the poore into iuſt conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, weed out, and root out from the city of the Lord, all vnprofitable members, inordinate walkers, diſſolute liuers: ſearch Ieruſalem with lights, for theſe linkers, in the theeuiſh corners of the City, which are the Deuils cloſets, wherein he ſits cloſe, ſtudying and contriuing all villany, and miſchiefe, and afterward put in execution: take heed you winke not at theſe, nouriſh them not, but ſuppreſſe them; let them not come in your way, except it be to puniſh them: <hi>hoc agite, principatum quemgeritis orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re;</hi> adorne your places with your carriage, in ſo good a place Doe much good, God hath put the ſword in thy hand to doe this buſineſſe, therefore thou muſt doe it; then goo on with cheerfulneſſe, and courage in thy place, the Lord ſhall be with thee, ſhew thy ſelfe a man.</p>
               <p>Particularly, the Miniſter of Gods word muſt be zealous of Doing good, painfully labouring, with wholſome do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, threathing the thunder-claps of Gods iudgements, againſt all impenitent workers of iniquity; and pouring the balme of Gilead into the wounds of the diſtreſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan, opening the myſtery of the word of life, whereby, many bee made wiſe vnto ſaluation; and that the man of God may be perfectly furniſhed to euery good worke.</p>
               <p>And in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> word, euery particular degree of men, high and low, rich and poore, publikely in the Church, priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the family, muſt exerciſe themſelues in doing of good, yeelding obedience to the commandements of God, and labouring in their lines and conuerſations to make a reall, yea a royall manifeſtation of the fayth which they profeſſe, by Doing of ſome good.</p>
               <p>But there is a more proper obiect of our Doing good, namely to the poore; wherein, that wee may not any way miſtake, the Scripture hath ſet downe certaine cautions,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16241:29"/>and confined vs to certaine limitations, ſummarily cou ched in that prouerbiall verſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſt modus in dando, quid, cur, cui, quomedo, quando.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beyond which bounds, wee may not paſſe. Let vs take a running view of them. Fiue rules are heere to bee obſerued in our Doing good.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. What we giue.</item>
                  <item>2. Why we giue.</item>
                  <item>3. To whom we giue.</item>
                  <item>4. How we giue.</item>
                  <item>5. When we giue.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. What. We muſt giue that which is our owne; honor the Lord with thy ſubſtance, not another mans; and with the firſt fruits of thine increaſe, Prou. 3.9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Why muſt we giue. Becauſe God commands it; loue the ſtranger;<note place="margin">Leu. 19.34.</note> then loued when releeued; becauſe Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it. <hi>Date cleemoſynam,</hi> Luc. 11.41. hee that giues all requires but ſome, a cup of cold water, a cruſt of bread; and becauſe the ſpirit commends it; for a ſacrifice wherewith God is well pleaſed, Heb. 13.16. The Rabbines ſay, tithe and be rich: the Lord, giue and be rich; he that giueth to the poore, lendeth to the Lord, Prou. 19.17. <hi>Qui miſeretur proximo, foeneratur Domino.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. To whom muſt we giue? To all, Gal. 6.10. While we haue time let vs doe good to all; eſpecially to the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith. Thus God is rich in goodneſſe vnto all, euen his enemies, in cauſing the ſunne to riſe vpon the iuſt and vniuſt, Matt. 5. but eſpecially to the faythfull (which in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the ſmall number are called a houſhold) theſe Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid preferred. O Lord, my goodnes extendeth not to thee, but to the Saints that are in the earth, my delight is in them, Pſal. 16.2.3. And as touching the poore, wee muſt make diſcretion Steward of the Kitchin, leſt we prooue our ſelues guilty of fooliſh pity; for there are of poore
<list>
                     <item>1. impotent,</item>
                     <item>2. labouring.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Seeke out theſe in the backe lanes, if they ſeeke not thee, and releeue them; but for the idle poore, and ſturdy poore
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16241:29"/>giue them not, except it be a whip and a paſport; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the more liberall, the fewer beggars in Iſrael.</p>
               <p n="4">4. How muſt wee giue? The Apoſtle hath directed. The Lord loueth a cheerefull giuer, 2. Cor. 9.7. God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a willing giuer. Againe, abundantly: hee that ſoweth ſparingly, ſhall reape ſparingly; and he that ſoweth plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, ſhall reap plentifully. To this end the oyle of our cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity muſt be compounded rightly. As Moſes was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, to put into the oyle, certaine ſpices, ſo God would haue euery Chriſtian Almeſgiuer, to play the Druggiſt; firſt our almes muſt be like myrrh, which diſtils from the tree without cutting or inciſion: ſo muſt charity without compulſion. Secondly, Cinamon; hot in taſte, hot in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration: ſo muſt our almes, neither ſtone. cold as Nabal, nor lukewarme as Laodicea; but hot, as it is ſayd of Iohn Baptiſt of Conſtantinople, whoſe daily practiſe was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the poore. Thirdly Caſſia; as ſweet as the former, but low, the embleme of humility; ſo giue, but not vaineglori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. Fourthly, Calamus; an odoriferous powder, but of a fragill reed. So giue, but acknowledge thy weakeneſſe; thinke it not meritorious: <hi>periculoſa domus corum qui meritis ſperant,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard;</hi> dangerous is that houſe, which thinks to winne heauen by keeping houſe; dangerous becauſe ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inous, no, ſay you are vnprofitable ſeruants. But leſt I grow tedious. Fiftly, conſider the time when we muſt giue: while we haue time, during our life; thus was Dorcas ſayd to bee full of good workes while ſhe liued. Salomon ſo aduifeth Prou. 3.28. Say not vnto thy neighbour, goe and come againe to morrow, and I will giue thee, when thou haſt it by thee. Our Sauiours action muſt be our imitation; and hee ſayth, I muſt worke the workes of him that ſent mee, while it is called to day. The night commeth wherein none can worke, Ioh. 9.4. To day if you will heare his voyce. The time paſt cannot bee recalled, the time to come vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, the time preſent only ours. He therefore ſpake not amiſſe, that ſo ſpake:</p>
               <q>Da tua dum tua ſunt, poſt mortem tune tua non ſunt.</q>
               <p>Death is the worlds ſtrict dore-keeper, who as we brought
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16241:30"/>nothing, will narrowly ſearch vs that we ſhall carry no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with vs; wherefore while we haue time, let vs diuide our goods, and deale our dole, with Zacheus, that ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may come to our houſe here, and when we leaue our houſe, we may goe to ſaluation hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> So then to come to a third vſe of the Doctrine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and proued, me thinks here come within com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of iuſt cenſure, diuers Chriſtians (as they eſteeme themſelues) to be ſharply reproued. Firſt Nullifidians, and Merit-mongers, whom we leaue on the left hand (as Paul left Cyprus.) Secondly carnall Goſpellers, and Solifidians on the right, for neither of theſe doe either at all, or (at leaſt) this good aright. In vain ſhall any thinks to come to heaven by the ladder of workes, ſince in Chriſt, neither circumciſion nor vncircumciſion auaileth any thing. No religious order in the world, but faith alone without truſt in works, auaileth before God.</p>
               <p>Yet on the other ſide, the heauens cannot bee ſcaled without a ladder, which although it be Chriſt, yet ſome of the lower ſtaues and higher to, are pinned faſt with good workes, whereby, all ſlothfull and idle perſons are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; affirming that if faith alone iuſtifie, then let vs barely truſt in God, but not be Doing of good: not ſo ye careleſſe generation, enemies of grace, for faith is operatiue, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by loue: faith is reſembled to fire, which is operatiue; fire cannot be without heat, and light; the greater fire the greater heat, the leſſer fire the leſſer heat; no fire no heat, no heat no fire.</p>
               <p>But it may be ſaid of too many, and thoſe (as they take themſelues) none of the coldeſt Chriſtians, or profeſſors amongſt vs, as one ſometime of the Monks of his time, that their faſts were fat, and prayers leane, their faith is hot, their loue cold: they ſay they truſt in God better then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; yet doe leſſe good then others; it may bee ſaid of ſuch, as the witty Grecian ſpake of extreame tall men, that they were Cypreſſe trees, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, faire and tall but fruitleſſe, oh ſhame that the child of heauen ſhould reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hell! which hath fire, but that fire hath no light.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:16241:30"/>
I feare we haue too may ſuch firebrands of hell, that haue a flaſhing fire of faith in their tongues, but the fire of their faith makes not their loue boile; Lazarus ſhall haue more diuinity then humanity, twenty <hi>paternoſters,</hi> not one penny at their hands: Theſe mens light ſhineth not out before men, and therefore are leaueleſſe trees, empty clouds, waterleſſe wels (like the ſumptuos Sumptermule of that vaineglorious Cardinall) ſeeming without wondrous rich, but nothing within ſaue old ſhooes and rubbiſh; or like Adonibezek, want their thumbs: but Gods Prieſt muſt haue, not only the Vrim of ſcience, but Thummim of conſcience on his breaſt, and in his skirts, not only bels, a ſounding profeſſion, but pomegranates alſo, a fruitfull deuotion: faith and loue on the altar of the heart, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer goe out, like that ſtone in <hi>Plinie,</hi> which being once made hot, could neuer be cold. If it be otherwiſe (and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſo it is) whatſoeuer they boaſt of their faith, they are but hypocrites in the ſight of God: like that <hi>beſtia phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macopolae,</hi> wherewith <hi>Iulian</hi> twitted <hi>Auſten,</hi> a beaſt preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of great vertue ouernight, that ere morning was come, had deuoured her ſelfe: or laſtly, like that curſed fig-tree, therefore curſed becauſe it was fruitleſſe.</p>
               <p>Thus in generall; more particularly, to runne through all degrees of men, it is pitifull to ſee (and therefore great reaſon to complaine) that this practicall politicall part of Chriſtian obedience, not only in rectifying our owne courſes, and Doing good our ſelues, but alſo in reprouing, repreſſing, and reforming the irregularities of others, and the ſinnes of the time is commonly neglected of all:</p>
               <p>How many neuter-paſſiue Magiſtrates, meale-mouthed Officers, ſcar-crow Conſtables haue we now a daies? that are ſo farre from Phineas his zeale, to ſlay offenders <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> that they want Moſes his courage to ſlay ſinne in groſſe offenders. <hi>ſalvo iure:</hi> and herein pardon my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for <hi>aures omnium pulſo, conſcientias ſingulorum conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio;</hi> I ſpeake to the eares of all in generall, and appeale to the conſcience of euery one in particular if this bee not ſo: many of them are ſo farre from reprouing, that they are
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16241:31"/>content with ſinne, and yeeld conſent to it, that ſo they may take vp ſinne vpon warrant, and commit it boldly, and ſo goe to the Deuill by authority. If this were not ſo, why are not the hurts of the daughter of Iudah healed? why are not the breaches of Sion ſtopped? why are not recuſants puniſhed? why is not the pot pulled from the noſe of the drunkard? why is not the Sabbath ſanctified? why are not our horrible blaſphemers, our ſhameleſſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicators, incorrigible drunkards, and the like profane li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious liuers, let blood with the ſharpe razor of repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, or ſtruck downe with a downe-right blow of condigne puniſhment, for their preſumption? What? is there no balme in Gilead, no Phyſitian there? yes, but they are (like Iobs friends) Phyſitians of no reckoning, Rephaims by name, Zamzummims indeed, who, whereas they ſhould be patrons and patternes of piety, and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as their places and callings require, and as leaders of the Vantgard, to ſtand in the forefront of Gods battell, againſt all Caananites, which cry downe holineſſe in towne and country; they either runne along with them, or rather lead them into the race of riot, or are buſied in boo-thalling, and foraging for themſelues, not caring for the ſhip of ſtate in generall, ſo they may be ſafe in the cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boat of their owne fortunes in particular. I am aſhamed to thinke and ſpeake how weakely the paralytick hands of our Magiſtrates are exerciſed in Doing of good in their places, by brandiſhing the ſword of iuſtice againſt the friends of Baal, Balaam, and Bacchus. Reſembling Oſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which haue great feathers, but no flight; or Iupitera block caſt among the frogs, whom at firſt they feared for the greatneſſe, but deſpiſed afterward for the ſtilneſſe. So that as <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> ſometime complained, that the power of their aduerſary <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> was greatly augmented by the Athenians ſlothfulnſſe: So may the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God complaine, that through the ſlothfulneſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſeneſſe, or wickedneſſe of many Magiſtrates, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Satan is exceedingly enlarged.</p>
               <p>Againe, to put that part of the wallet which hangeth
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16241:31"/>behind our backs, into open ſight, how is this duty of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good neglected, euen in many of vs? who neither feed liberally by charity, nor ſoundly by Doctrine, nor religiouſly by life, which made that proud fugitiue <hi>Campi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> as malitiouſly as ſpitefully, to ſay; <hi>miniſtris illorum nihil vilius.</hi> Heauen and earth can beare witneſſe that the Sunne neuer beheld a more learned, amore religious Cleargie, yet among ſo many pots of the Temple what maruell is it,<note place="margin">Doctor Hall.</note> if ſome be drie for want of liquor, others ruſty for want of vſe, others full of liquor without meat, others ſo full of meat that they want liquor: woe to thoſe corrupted ſonnes of Heli, which through inſufficiency or vnconſcionableneſſe, poure contempt on their owne faces: Againe, for other degrees of men, how farre in their places from Doing that which is good, is plaine to behold. The Lawyer bee it knowne vnto all men, vſeth the Law vnlawfully, not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it a ſpeciall and ſpeedy remedy of wrongs, but an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine or trap to enſnare the weake and ſimple, trebling their fees of vniuſt gaine, and troubling the world with vniuſt ſuites.</p>
               <p>The Shopkeepers alſo, as we paſſe along, to caſt an eye of obſeruance on them, how righteous he is in his dealing, is eaſie to iudge, their houſes are as full of deceit as a cage of birds, if either lies, and oathes, or falſe lights, falſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, vniuſt and unconſcionable gaines may make men righteous, then there is no vnrighteouſneſſe in them.</p>
               <p>Laſtly; what doing of good our rich men practiſe now a daies, he that hath but halfe his ſight with one-eyed <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi> may cleerly ſee, for they are better a great deale at the rake, then at the pitchforke, as it is in the prouerbe, readier to pull and rake to them, then to lay out or giue any thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aurum habet Eccleſia, non ut ſervet, ſed ut eroget,</hi> but their greedy deſires of mony, increaſe faſter then their mony; our extortioners are not rooted in charity, their mindes are on their mines, that's the root, where they root, but if the Apoſtle ſpake true, Philargury is the root of all villany. Theſe ſell the ayre, take mony for time, contract with Satan, giue their ſoules for ſurety, and the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16241:32"/>Deuill keepes the bond till they pay in themſelues for the principalls.</p>
               <p>Doe our rich men reſemble Saint <hi>Bafil</hi> the great, who in a famine, did not only giue to the poore himſelfe, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted others to open their barnes and doe the like?</p>
               <p>Or <hi>William Warbam,</hi> ſometime Archbiſhop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, who was ſo liberall to the poore, that hee left but thrity peeces of gold behinde him, which pleaſed (as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus</hi> ſaith) him ſo well, that he ſaid; It is well I deſired alway to dye no richer.</p>
               <p>Or <hi>Philip Melancthon,</hi> who was out of a meane eſtate ſo bountifull, that euery houre ſome or other were relieued at his dore. Or es <hi>Dorcas,</hi> full of good works. Or as the Captaine Cornelius, and other holy men of God, Abraham, Lot, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Surely they are the greateſt part ſo farre from going out to meet the poore, (as Abraham met the three Angels vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne) that they turne their backs, and ſhut the dore vpon them, and inſtead of feaſting and refreſhing of them, with churliſh and crabbed words rate them away with hungry ſtomackes.</p>
               <p>No, no, their care is to build faire houſes, and when they haue done, to lock the dore and goe their waies, and leaue them empty: we haue a great many of theſe mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beggars in England, which where they ſhould doe moſt good (like butterflyes) are to be ſeene but once in a yeere, yet that is not to make a feaſt with Nabal at their ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhearing, nor to relieue their poore neighbours neere them, but to rack their rents, and enhaunſe their fines, to make themſelues very fine, <hi>&amp; finem facere,</hi> to vndoe the poore Tenant, to call Courts, to fill carts, to fence God out, and hedge the Deuill in.</p>
               <p>Giue? they are ſo farre from giuing, that like ſpunges, good muſt be wrung out of them perforce; like vnto Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal, churliſh and euill in their doings, which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they haue good cauſe,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.3.</note> yet are ſo farre from helping, that they ſay, who is Dauid, or what is the ſonne of Ieſſe? there be many ſeruants now a dayes, that breake away eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16241:32"/>one from his maſter; ſhall I then take my bread and fleſh that I haue killed for my ſhearers, and giue it to theſe whom I know not whence they be?</p>
               <p>Or like Cain <hi>nunquid ego fratris cuſtos?</hi> am I my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers keeper? Or like Iudas, <hi>ad quid perditio haec?</hi> to what end is this waſte? yea ſo farre are many from helping and relieuing them, that becauſe they are rich, they preſume they may tread them downe, &amp; oppreſſe them by authority, keepe back their maintenance, take away their meanes, as Ahab did poore Naboths Vineyard, and their life too, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if miſtris painted face Iezabel can beare rule; what are they not rich, art not thou a King? art not thou a Lord of that Mannor? are they not thy Tenants? bridle them and ſaddle them, and ſpurre them to death, to keepe the ſlaues downe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Yet I muſt confeſſe many rich men doe giue now adaies, but it is according to that rule formerly ſet downe. Surely no, for</p>
               <p>Firſt, there are that regard not what they giue, they giue that for which they deſerue no thanks, but ſhame; they feed the poore at another mans table, and make them free of another mans trencher: ſuch an almes-giuer was the Deuill, who would giue the world to our Sauiour, a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall almes, but out of Gods Exchequer, yet (as theſe) hee ſaid, all is mine, and to whom I pleaſe I giue it. So <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the ſixt gaue America to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> as in 88. the Pope gaue England to him to a great gift<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but out of the Indians and Chriſtians freehold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo indeed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny an vpſtart Gentleman giues, by keeping of a good houſe for his company, when like the lewes, he crucifies Chriſt in his poore Tenants, he feedeth ſome few poore as his wicket, and hath made many poore to furniſh his dreſſer; his charity reliues ten, his cruelty hath vndone ten thouſand. If euer the prouerbe be true, tis true in this; here is robbing of Peter to pay Paul.</p>
               <p>Secondly, there are that regard not why they giue, not out of any care to obey Gods Commandements; not out of any loue to their brethren, not out of any loue chiefely to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16241:33"/>Gods glory, or the like, but to get a name, to become fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, for oſtentation ſake, as the Scribes and Phariſees, theſe are obſtreperous benefactors, which cackle like hens and blow a trumpet in the ſtreets of their deeds, haue not I done this, giuen him that, preferred him to his liuing or place, did not I ſettle him? yes, but not out of any zeale to Gods glory, but for ſome by-reſpect, to make ſome other vſe of him in ſuch or ſuch occaſions, and ſeruice: but almes ſhold be like Oyle, which is ſilent in pouring downe, and maketh no noiſe, yet it lies aloft: So thou needeſt not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime thy owne worth, for he that ſeeth in ſecret, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thee openly. But becauſe there are more rare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haſten to the next.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, there are that giue and drop ſiluer, but not with diſcretion, to thoſe which either haue no need, or are not worthy. Some feed the Spaniel. I meane the Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, who neuer will leaue begging while any continues giuing: ſome feed the Gray hound, the riotous prodigall: ſome the Maſtife, the gullet theefe, ſtill gaping for more: ſome the Curre, the criticall ſlanderer, for whom the hooke is a fitter morſell then the bait: ſome to the Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, which ſtudy nothing but <hi>Apicius</hi> in his art of Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, whoſe greateſt manhood is ſeene at the table in quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering and caruing dead carkaſes; but this is giuing of the childrens meat to dogs, ſome againe to the poore, but not ſo made of God, but from the Deuils bones and books, cards, and dice, wine and women, and ſuch like husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry. —</p>
               <p>Fourthly, there are that regard not how they giue, they giue but with grudging, with pining, with pinching, with conſtraint, being drawne like a Beare to the ſtake, they part from a penny as from a drop of blood; nor will they be any further bountifull then the ſtatute law compels them.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, there are that giue, but regard nor the time, for either they giue when there is no need, or when they can no longer keepe: the poore ſhall be fed at their dore, when they are carryed to their graue, and ſo bee clothed when
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16241:33"/>they muſt be naked; for which charity, they are more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to their teſtament then will, for it ſhould not haue beene giuen if it could haue beene kept.</p>
               <p>And for this they are more beholding to their death-bed then them; where it often falleth out, that the poore mourne indeed not ſo much for their death as for that they dyed no ſooner.</p>
               <p>Here is a generation of crooked, carnall and faithleſſe giuers, like Saint Iohns generation of vipers, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they continue giuers, ſhall not be gainers, whom yet I forewarne to fly from the wrath which is to come, by bringing forth fruits worthy of amendment of life: Let this laſtly be the vſe for obedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Wherefore dearely beloued, whilſt the wizards of the world (like to that couetous Cardinall which preferred his portion in <hi>Paris,</hi> before his part in Paradiſe,) exerciſe themſelues wholly in ioyning houſe to houſe, and land to land, and account it the greateſt point of cunning to gaine and retaine, good eſtates, good farmes, good fields, good friends, good houſes, good horſes, good clothes, euery thing elſe good for themſelues, but neuer exerciſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in Doing good to others; let vs all of vs if we would be accounted godly, wiſe, and prouident indeed, be moſt of all carefull and earneſt for the world which is to come; wherewith, that we may be really poſſeſſed, and ſo royally bleſſed: let vs neuer be weary of well-doing, for in due time we ſhall reape if we faint not.</p>
               <p>And for you whom it hath pleaſed God to endow with a more liberall portion of the things of this life; ſo to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it the beſt Chriſtian policie, by your good works on earth, to lay vp treaſures for your ſelues in heauen, and and euery day to bring in ſomewhat into Gods Exchequer, as the Iſraelites into the Tabernacle, the remembrance whereof may long after both in life and death comfort you.</p>
               <p>It is an hard ſentence of ſome Caſuiſts concerning their fellowes, that few rich mens Confeſſors ſhall be ſaued: for that hapily they dawbe vp their conſciences with vntem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16241:34"/>morter, ſoothing them vp in their ſinnes: let this be the care of thoſe whom it may concerne. For vs, wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be faithfull to God and you, and therefore round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell you. Doe good, O ye rich men, if euer you looke to receiue good, if you be not rich in good works, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be rich in heauen: as <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſaid that he made himſelfe rich, while he enriched his friends; ſo lay vp treaſures for your ſelues in heauen, whiles you make the poore your friends on earth. If you looke for the intereſt of glory in heauen, you muſt pay the principall of beneficence in earth.</p>
               <p>Be not therefore like mount Gilboah fruitleſſe and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren.</p>
               <p>Be not like the Oliue tree, which when Goats lick it, fruitfulneſſe doth leaue it.</p>
               <p>Be not like a Vine tree, the more boughs the leſſer and ſewer grapes.</p>
               <p>Be not like a Cloue tree, ſo hot by nature, to rob the neighbour plants of moiſture.</p>
               <p>But be thou like that tree of Dauid, planted by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſide (by regeneration) bringing forth fruit in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (by ſanctification) whoſe leaues ſhall not fall (by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation) Goe thou and doe likewiſe, bring forth and multiply; if euer thou hope to be planted in the new Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, thou muſt bring forth twelue manner of fruits, yea the leaues muſt bee beneficiall. Bring forth then not flowers or flouriſhes, bloſſomes or ſemblances onely, but fruits; not fruit of the world, for that's folly; nor fruit of the fleſh, that's frailty; nor fruit of the eyes, that's fancy; but meet fruits for contrition of heart, reformation of life, ſanctification of ſoule.</p>
               <p>Let not the children of this world, excell the children of light: they are fruitfull but not beneficiall, <hi>multum ſed mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> there is greene fruit of imperfectneſſe, red fruit of blood thirſtineſſe, yeallow fruit of gall and bitterneſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> colored fruit of drunkenneſſe, earth-colored fruit of couvetouſneſſe, pale-colored fruit of laſciuiouſneſſe, theſe are trees but not of Gods planting theſe the Deuill plants,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16241:34"/>ſuggeſtion waters, continuance encreaſeth, neceſſity ripens, iudgement gathers, and bell burneth.</p>
               <p>Be not thou like vnto thoſe Indian Pandorae of whom it is reported, that they haue white hoare heads in their youth, and black haire in their age.</p>
               <p>Or like <hi>Hermogenes,</hi> of whom <hi>Antiochus</hi> ſaid, that hee was in his childhood an old man, and in his old age a child; be not thou more expert vnder thy Catechizers in principles of piety, and as thou groweſt vpward in yeeres to grow downewards in grace: like the ſhe Wolfe, which they ſay, hath an yeerly defect in her procreation: the firſt time ſhe beareth fiue the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d foure, the third three, the fourth two, the fifth one, and then remaineth barren: the child of God muſt not ſo doe, he muſt goe from ſtrength to ſtrength, and grow from grace to grace, bringing forth moſt good in their age, like Caleb, ſtrong in his old age for gouernment and warre, like Ruth ſhewing more good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the latter end then beginning: like the Sunne in the Firmament which is ſwifteſt at his ſetting; ſo the ſonnes of God muſt be beſt at their ending. Let a good Chriſtian be like vnto a ſheepe, in which euery thing is good and vſefull, his fleece good, his fell good, his fleſh good, his entrals, yea all is good: and ſo a ſanctified Chriſtian is a ſeruant to all the ſeruants of God, euery good gift in him is profitable; to ſome he lendeth his fleece, clothing the naked; to ſome his bread, in feeding the hungry; to ſome his eyes, in becomming a guide to the blinde; to ſome his ſtrength, in becomming feet to the lame; to ſome his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, in becomming an inſtructer to the ſimple; at all times, and to all perſons, in all places, Doing of good.</p>
               <p>Wherefore let vs be of <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> minde in <hi>Euripides,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. let vs ſee our Tombes honored by Doing good while we liue; this is the way to make our names truly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and our memories eternall; here laſting, hereafter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting; here renowned among men, there crowned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Saints and Angels, in the Kingdome of glory.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
